<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A vindication of the Lords prayer, as a formal prayer, and by Christ's institution to be used by Christians as a prayer: against the antichristian practice and opinion of some men. Wherein, also their private and ungrounded zeal is discovered, who are very strict for the observation of the Lords Day, and make so light of the Lords prayer. By Meric Casaubon, D.D. one of the prebandaries of C.C. Canterb.</title>
            <author>Casaubon, Meric, 1599-1671.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 134 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 68 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A81232</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C817</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1921_3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R209969</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99868813</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99868813</idno>
            <idno type="VID">121169</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A81232)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 121169)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 239:E1921[3])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A vindication of the Lords prayer, as a formal prayer, and by Christ's institution to be used by Christians as a prayer: against the antichristian practice and opinion of some men. Wherein, also their private and ungrounded zeal is discovered, who are very strict for the observation of the Lords Day, and make so light of the Lords prayer. By Meric Casaubon, D.D. one of the prebandaries of C.C. Canterb.</title>
                  <author>Casaubon, Meric, 1599-1671.</author>
                  <author>Grotius, Hugo, 1583-1645.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 112, [6] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T.R. for Thomas Johnson at the Key in St. Paul's Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>[6] pages at end = letter, signed H. Grotius.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "August".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Lord's prayer --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:121169:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A VINDICATION OF THE LORDS PRAYER, AS A FORMAL PRAYER, And by <hi>CHRIST'S INSTIT<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>TION</hi> To be uſed by Chriſtians as a Prayer; againſt the Antichriſtian Practice and Opinion of ſome men.</p>
            <p>Wherein, <hi>Alſo their private and ungrounded</hi> zeal <hi>is diſcovered, who are very ſtrict for the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of the</hi> Lords Day, <hi>and make ſo light of the</hi> LORDS PRAYER.</p>
            <p>By MERIC CASAUBON, D. D. one of the Prebandaries of <hi>C. C. Canterb.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> printed by <hi>T.R.</hi> for <hi>Thomas Johnſon</hi> at the <hi>Key</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church yard, 1660.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:121169:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:121169:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE firſt occaſion of this <hi>Treatiſe</hi> (Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Reader,) was the Relation of a ſtrange affront done publickly unto Chriſt, or if you will more punctually, to the <hi>Lords Prayer,</hi> in the chief Church of <hi>Oxford,</hi> by one that had then (under uſurping Powers) the chief Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of that famous Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity. When the thing was done, (for I have heard it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by divers) I know not
<pb facs="tcp:121169:3"/>preciſely: this I know, that ever ſince I heard of it, I never was at reſt in my mind, though it might be a good while before I had the opportunity, until I had written ſomewhat in <hi>Vindication</hi> of it. It did trouble me, that any man profeſſing Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, ſhould ſo much diſhonour Chriſt; much more, that he durſt (an argument of diſmal times;) do it in ſuch a place: moſt of all, that when he did it, ſo many Chriſtians then preſent, had the patience to ſee it, or the confidence to tarry in the place, where ſuch an Affront was done unto him they call <hi>Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our.</hi> Since that, much hath been added, to my indignation both,
<pb facs="tcp:121169:3"/>&amp; admiration, when I have been told, that many that profeſſed another way, and went under another Title, notwithſtanding what they had ſaid of it publick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, did ſhamefully comply with the Court-Preachers and Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſites of the times, and had gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven it over, they alſo, many, or moſt of them, I know ſomewhat is ſaid in their defence; but that ſomewhat (if I be not mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaken in this <hi>Treatiſe</hi>) makes the caſe rather worſe: and if ſuch poor ſhifts may ſerve for ſo fowl Acts, let us talk no more of <hi>Scripture</hi> againſt <hi>Papiſts,</hi> or ony others: I know nothing ſo groſs, but <hi>Scripture</hi> may be pretended for it, with as much
<pb facs="tcp:121169:4"/>or more probability. What is here preſented unto thee, Good Reader, was written and ready for the Preſs, above a year ago, as ſome can witneſs, that have ſeen it, and read it. How it happened, that it was not printed before; one occaſion was, that I have been often away; and when in Town, not always at leaſure to think of it. But if it be now ſeaſonable, (as I hope it is) it is nedleſs to make any further <hi>Apology,</hi> why not before. Only this it is fit thou ſhouldſt know, that if it had been now to do, (ſince this bleſſed alteration, for which God make us all thankfull) my expreſſions might have been
<pb facs="tcp:121169:4"/>fuller and plainer, in ſome pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. In a place, where I ſay, <hi>this might happen to them, as a Judgement, for oppoſing, yea, perſecuting ſomewhat, once the glory of the Engliſh Reformation, and the beſt of things that have been</hi> (by humane contrivance and Authority) <hi>eſtabliſhed among men;</hi> I hope I ſhall be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, to mean this of the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh <hi>Liturgie</hi> or <hi>Book of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Prayers.</hi> Indeed that is my meaning: and I hope, I ſay no more of it, than I can (with the help of God) make good againſt any that ſhall pretend to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe it, by either reaſon, or Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture. Yet I know, even of late, what out-cries are made
<pb facs="tcp:121169:5"/>againſt it. Will the Reader give me leave, to give him a taſte of their objections? It doth much trouble them, that by it, ſome Leſſons out of the <hi>Apocrypha</hi> are appointed. Well, if that were thought fit to be altered, that is little or nothing to the ſubſtance of the book. But is this ſuch a thing in the mean time, that deſerves ſuch out-cries? O, but things fabu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, falſe, contradictorie out of them are read. Indeed this were a grievous imputation, if they were propoſed unto the people, as any part of the Word of God. Though this we may ſay withal, that many things may appear falſe, ridiculous,
<pb facs="tcp:121169:5"/>contradictory, at firſt hearing, as they may be ſet out, which upon better examination, will not be found ſo. But if no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing muſt be read or heard in a Church, but what is unqueſtio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nably true, and good, that is, divine: Lord, what will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of <hi>Sermons</hi> then, ſuch eſpecially as we have had of late years, in many places? Men in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed make bold to call them generally, <hi>the Word of God;</hi> but I hope no body is ſo ſtupid, as to think all treaſon, blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, non-ſenſe, falſe doctrine, delivered out of Pulpits, to be truly the Word of God. But <hi>Sermons,</hi> ſome will ſay per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hance, are the Ordinance of
<pb facs="tcp:121169:6"/>God. However, ſo much will follow, that ſomewhat may be tolerated, (in the Church) for a greater good; that is lyable to ſome inconveniences. And I think no ſober impartial man will deny, but that <hi>Wiſdome, Eccleſiaſticus,</hi> and other Books that go under that title of <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crypha,</hi> do afford as good things for the Inſtruction of people, as many <hi>Sermons</hi> uſually, that are not of the worſt. Well: what are <hi>Prayers,</hi> that are made <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempore,</hi> or would be thought ſo, at leaſt: ſo much in requeſt in theſe late times, are they not lyable to the ſame incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venience? If any man ſhall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre hereupon, that therefore
<pb facs="tcp:121169:6"/>none but preſcribed <hi>Prayers,</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed by publick Authority, are ſo fit to be uſed in a Church; I for my part ſhould readily ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe; but I doubt the neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the inference, will not ſo eaſily be granted by all men. Truly, It might have been ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, that the ſad experience of theſe late times, ſince every man, <hi>Papiſts</hi> only, and <hi>Prela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical men</hi> excepted, have been left to their liberty, would have diſpoſed men <hi>truly zealous</hi> for the <hi>Proteſtant Intereſt,</hi> to a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Opinion of former times, when, to the grief of the Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries of it; <hi>the Proteſtant</hi> Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion here flouriſhed; and to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain now with joy, what
<pb facs="tcp:121169:7"/>once in peeviſhneſs, and love of Novelty, they did not ſo much care for. But <hi>I</hi> doubt there is ſomewhat elſe in it. What that is, (if not already too viſible to the world;) I rather leave to their own conſciences. One <hi>paſſage,</hi> or Teſtimony (for the Eminency of the <hi>Author,</hi> and his exquiſit Judgement in ſuch things; our <hi>late Gracious Soveraign,</hi> now a glorious <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr</hi> in heaven;) <hi>I</hi> would have added to this <hi>Treatiſe,</hi> where the <hi>Reader</hi> ſhall think moſt conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient. It was not then in my thoughts, when I was upon it; though indeed the Book highly deſerve, never to be out of our hands. The words are, <hi>Some
<pb facs="tcp:121169:7"/>men I hear, are ſo impatient not to uſe, in all their Devotions, their own invention and gifts, as they not only diſuſe, (as too many) but wholly cast away and contemn the</hi> Lords Prayer, <hi>whoſe great guilt is, that it is the warrant and original pattern of all ſet Liturgies in the Chriſtian Church.</hi>
               <note place="bottom">† King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, in His Sacred Meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, <hi>ch.</hi> 16. <hi>upon the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance againſt the</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon prayer book.</note> 
               <hi>I</hi> will not excuſe my ſelf for this paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage: in the reſt, if the Reader think <hi>I</hi> have ſaid more than <hi>I</hi> needed, <hi>I</hi> crave his pardon, and bid him <hi>Farewell.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb facs="tcp:121169:8"/>
            <head>A POSTSCRIPT.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>SInce this was printed, and ready to come forth, a book (or</hi> Paſquil <hi>ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, it is ſo full of railing:) intitled,</hi> The Common Prayer Book unmask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>&amp;c. came to my ſight, and I thought my ſelf engaged by the Argument, to look upon it. It is ſuch a peece of exquiſit</hi> Non-ſenſe, <hi>of groundleſse impudent So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiſtry, with bitter rayling, and much profane jeering all along, that</hi> I <hi>muſt needs think, they that have patience (excepten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged by ſome particular conſideration) to read ſuch ſtuffe, without detestation, may as plauſibly be perſwaded to ſing</hi> Ballads, <hi>in ſtead of</hi> Holy Hymes, <hi>and to think that men ſerve God beſt in Tap-houſes-The whole ſtrength of the Book lyeth in this:</hi> The <hi>Maſſe-Book, Breviaries, &amp;c.</hi> are idolatrous popiſh-Books; therefore whatſoever is taken out of them, (or may be ſuppoſed to be taken out of them, becauſe to be found there) is popiſh, and idolatrous. <hi>Now a good
<pb facs="tcp:121169:8"/>part both of the</hi> Old <hi>and</hi> New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>beſides the whole Book of</hi> Pſalmes, <hi>is to be found in</hi> Maſs-books, <hi>and</hi> Breviaries: <hi>Is any man ſo blind that dooh not ſee what will follow? And is it not the ſame reaſon for many godly prayers ond forms: (not to ſpeak of</hi> Ceremonies, <hi>though it be true of them alſo) that were in uſe in time of pureſt Chriſtianity, long before</hi> Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>was heard of; yet to be found in</hi> Maſs-books <hi>and</hi> Breviaries? <hi>Or is it the bare word</hi> Maſs, <hi>that turneth all into Idolatry? why might not it be a good word, whatever it is now, a thouſand years ago? Many ages are not yet paſſed, when</hi> Canticles, <hi>or the</hi> Song of Songs, (<hi>as it is in the Original,) was called in</hi> Engliſh, <hi>the</hi> Ballad of Ballads. <hi>Now many, if not moſt</hi> ballads, <hi>we now ſo call, are profane, or ridiculous; and that word now, a word of Scorn; therefore the</hi> Canticles, <hi>or</hi> Song of Songs, <hi>ſhall be no longer part of Scripture, but meer Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry. Certainly, it muſt be granted, that
<pb facs="tcp:121169:9"/>wiſe Governours ſee much more, than or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary men: elſe, ſuch ſenſleſſe impious ſtuffe, a man would think, would not be permitted to be publick. But, what is all this, may ſome ſay, perchance, to the</hi> Lords Prayer, <hi>our subject? Alas! who ſeeth not, if all that is in</hi> Miſſals <hi>and</hi> Breviaries, <hi>or ſay, taken out of them,</hi> (im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately <hi>perchance, not</hi> originally,) <hi>be idolatrous; then, we know what muſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of the</hi> Lords Prayer, <hi>being there more than once upon ſeveral occaſions, and the firſt thing there that offers it ſelf to the view, in ſome of thoſe Books. This did ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige me to take ſome notice of the book: and ſo, I have done.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAg. 4. l. 7. r. whom. p. 18. l. 7. r. <hi>independents.</hi> p. 19. l. 2. r. <hi>tranſſubſt.</hi> p. 29. l. 17. r. end of f.. p. 32. l. 2. r. had. p. 54. l. 12. r. <hi>Enthuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſm,</hi> p. 80. l. 5. r do but <hi>lat.</hi> p. 81. l. 10. r. <hi>quaeram.</hi> p. 92. 11. r. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 66.11.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:121169:9"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A</hi> VINDICATION OF THE <hi>LORDS PRAYER,</hi> As a formal Prayer, and by Chriſts Inſtitution to be uſed by Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, as a Prayer; againſt the Antichriſtian Practiſe, and opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions of ſome.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E will forbear all Prefaces, and Rhetorical inſinuations, and haſten to the main buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. Truth may need ſuch ſometimes, by reaſon of mens infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities:
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:121169:10"/>and there be examples in Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, that may contend with the choiceſt Rhetorick, humane Authors afford, to juſtifie it, if need were. But in ſuch a caſe as <hi>I</hi> conceive this is, where com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſenſe, beſt reaſon; Authority, divine and humane; all that can be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired in a cauſe, are ſo manifeſtly vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, the beſt Rhetorick we can uſe, is to uſe no Rhetorick at all. It is the nature of Truth, to be moſt lovely, when ſeen naked: but it is not the luck of all Truth, to carry ſo much light, and luſtre with it, as will pierce thorow all Obſtacles, and make it viſible to all eyes. I hope it is the luck of this, that we contend for here: the Reader will quickly ſee, let him but read; I will not ſay without prejudice, (for that is not to be hoped) but not obſtinate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reſolved againſt the ingenuity of his confeſſion, though his conſcience be convicted.</p>
            <p>And here in the firſt place, we pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, we pretend not to write againſt
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:121169:10"/>any, who ſay, or teach, that what Chriſt hath commanded, ſo command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed without limitation of time or place, abſolutely and generally to be obſerved, ought not to be done by men that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs <hi>Christianity.</hi> There is no man ſo ſimple, but would preſently make this inference: This were to deny him in deed, whom we profeſs to honour and worſhip in words. Except we ſhould perchance eſtabliſh ſuch a power upon Earth, equivalent or ſuperiour to the power of Chriſt: a power to abrogate, or ratifie, at pleaſure, what is command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: <hi>Which oppoſeth and exalteth it ſelf above all that is called God,</hi> &amp;c. 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.4. How far this may belong to the Pope of <hi>Rome,</hi> who by his Canoniſts and others, doth take upon himſelf to have a power, <hi>Supra &amp; contra omne jus: contra jus naturale gentium; civile, huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num, divinum,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>contra Apoſtolum: Vetus Testamentum,</hi> &amp;c. to make <hi>de pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cato non peccatum, &amp; de non peccato pecca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um:</hi> how far I ſay, the Pope of <hi>Rome</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:121169:11"/>may be concerned in that place of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, I will not enquire. There be even of that ſide (profeſſed Papiſts) that have laid it to his charge, and applyed thoſe very words unto him. But it is not to our purpoſe to enquire: They are not Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, who we have to do with. We ſay therefore once again, We do not pretend to write againſt any, who main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain poſitively Chriſt ſhould not be obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: Or yet more particularly; not againſt any, who acknowledging theſe words of Chriſt, recorded <hi>Mat.</hi> 6. and <hi>Luk.</hi> 11. <hi>Our Father which art in Heaven,</hi> &amp;c. to be a preſcript form of <hi>Prayer;</hi> forbid us, and forbear themſelves, to uſe it as a <hi>Prayer:</hi> but againſt them, who allow not theſe words to be a <hi>Prayer,</hi> but a bare direction or platform of <hi>Prayer</hi> only: and upon that account, forbid, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear, as I have ſaid: who therefore will be ready to ſay, The queſtion is not properly of honour, or diſhonour done unto Chriſt, but of the right uſe, or underſtanding of his words.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:121169:11"/>
            <p> This may ſeem plauſible at firſt hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. But here I muſt deſire the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to conſider; that ſcarce ever was any opinion ſo falſe, or ſo impious, but men could find ſome words to ſet it out in another ſhape, if we will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent our ſelves with a ſuperficial view; or will look at a diſtance through ſuch proſpectives, as ſhall be put into our hands. We charge the Papiſts with impiety, for denying to ordinany Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians the uſe of Gods Word. They will ſay, they honour the Scripture, in keeping them from it, who, (through ignorance and ſimplicity) are more likely to abuſe it, than to make that uſe of it, for which it was given. That they were given us to do good, being committed unto ſuch hands as have skill to handle them; not to do hurt, w<hi rend="sup">ch.</hi> in the hands of ignorant, illiterate people, they are moſt likely. If good words and fair pretences will ſerve the turn, it cannot be denyed, but, in this cauſe, ſuch will eaſily be found, to make it plauſible: though no cauſe
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:121169:12"/>can leſs pretend to ſolidity of reaſon, (if we come to the tryal of either Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture or Antiquity) to make it true. Again, we charge them of Sacriledge and Impiety in maiming the Sacrament of the <hi>Lords Supper</hi> of one eſſential part, whilſt they keep ordinary people from the uſe of the Cup. The queſtion is not, what we can prove, but what they pretend. No ſuch thing as we lay to their Charge, I am ſure, that can be called either Sacriledge, or Impiety. The very Anabaptiſts, the rankeſt of them, (the <hi>Alumbradoes</hi> of <hi>Spain,</hi> or <hi>Quakers</hi> of <hi>England</hi>) who deny and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe all Scriptures; can we charge them of any impietie, if they may tell their own tale, and be believed without any further reaſoning? They will ſay, They honour, though not what we call <hi>Scripture:</hi> yet, <hi>the word of God,</hi> as much as any; that is, their inſpirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and raptures, and the Oracles of their own breaſt, their inward light; which they pretend to be the only true <hi>Word.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:121169:12"/>
            <p> Since therefore it is certain, that no opinion can be ſo impious in it ſelf, but it may be masked with words able, if not to make it plauſible and popular; yet, to hide the impiety: laying aſide what is pretended, as altogether imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent: we will come to the true ſtate of the queſtion, which we conceive to be this.</p>
            <p>Whether it may, or doth clearly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, by the plain literal obvious ſenſe, or conſtruction of Scripture; confirmed by all circumſtances of the Context; all probabilitie of humane ratiocination: the ſenſe and practiſe of all Chriſtians, ſince the very beginning of Chriſtianity, (ſo far as can be traced by Hiſtory) in all ages, in all places; that theſe words, <hi>Our Father,</hi> &amp;c. as ſet down in St. <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew,</hi> and St. <hi>Luke,</hi> were preſcribed by our <hi>LORD</hi> and <hi>SAVIOUR JESUS CHRIST,</hi> as a very form of <hi>Prayer,</hi> to be uſed by all profeſſing Chriſtianity, in thoſe very words, as a <hi>Prayer;</hi> yea, or noe.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:121169:13"/>
            <p> A queſtion of very great moment, as I apprehend it, the conſequent, or conſequence whereof; if the affirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive part of it be proved, will be,</p>
            <p>Firſt, that they who either by their example, or perſwaſions, bereave Chriſtians of it, are guilty (Prayer being a thing of ſuch conſequence in Religion) of horrible, deteſtable ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criledge: and may ſeem themſelves (to others) to renounce thereby to no ſmall part of Chriſtianity. We ſpeak to, and of profeſt Miniſters only in all this Diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>Secondly, whilſt it may probably be conceived, that a main reaſon that leads them unto this, is a great opinion they have of, or to their own conceptions in praying; which they therefore (in ordinary conſtruction of reaſon) muſt be thought to prefer before this form; this form, I ſay, by ſuch undeniable, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>controlable, (to common ſenſe and found reaſon) evidence of Scripture made, and preſcribed by Chriſt himſelf; (The
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:121169:13"/>Son of God, in whom <hi>all the Treaſures of Wiſdome are hidden,</hi> &amp;c.) hence it will follow, that they are guilty (though I hope not intended by them) yet guilty of high Blaſphemy againſt <hi>CHRIST,</hi> their God and Saviour.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, whileſt they ſeek evaſions againſt ſuch evidence of Scripture: ſuch evidence, as no other point, or doctrine of Chriſtianity, can pretend unto greater: it muſt needs follow, that by this their example, they give a moſt pernicious example to the moſt perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Hereticks, of preſent, or future ages, to ſhift all Scriptures, though never ſo clear againſt them, and do much countenance the Blaſphemies of ſome Papiſts, in calling them a <hi>Noſe of Wax,</hi> &amp;c. as alſo, ſtop or obſtruct their own mouths for ever ſpeaking againſt Quakers and Anabaptiſts, who certainly may pretend to as much ground of reaſon for denying all Scriptures, as any can, for denying the uſe of <hi>the Lords Prayer,</hi> as a Prayer unto Chriſtians;
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:121169:14"/>ſo demonſtrably grounded upon Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, commanded by Chriſt himſelf, confirmed by the practiſe of all Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans in the world.</p>
            <p>This is the true Eſtate of the queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as I apprehend. If any think fit to add, in the laſt place; That in caſe we come ſhort of our proofs, and cannot make our charge good, we muſt needs be guilty, either of inexcuſable igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, or intolerable uncharitableneſs, or both: I am content.</p>
            <p>If any ſhall think I have uſed ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravation in it, I am ſorry. My con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience doth bear me witneſs, I intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it not. I pray God heartily it may never be laid to their charge; as I ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily believe, that none of theſe things are really intended by them. But in a buſineſs of this nature, where I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the honour of Chriſt, and the good of all Chriſtians, ſo much intereſted; I think I ſhould unworthily prevaricate, if I ſhould not uſe plainneſs of words, and call <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as the old ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:121169:14"/>is. But this I have ſaid of my <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief,</hi> as to their intention: <hi>I</hi> mean it of ſuch, as are true Chriſtians in the main Fundamentals. As for the profeſt <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts, Quakers, Enthuſiaſts,</hi> or howe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver called, who have apoſtatized from the right ſaith: ſuch, as they frequently blaſpheme againſt the <hi>Perſon;</hi> ſo no wonder, if they frequently and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſely blaſpheme the <hi>Prayer</hi> of Chriſt. <hi>As I</hi> have heard it reported of ſome, (ſome years ago, great pretenders to the ſpirit of prayer) they ſhould often ſay, If Chriſt were alive again (con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſant in earth amongſt men; intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>I</hi> ſuppoſe:) he would be aſhamed of that prayer. Others have been heard, (wretched Miſcreants!) to ſay, they thanked God they had forgotten it. As bad or worſe hath been ſaid of the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture in general, we need not wonder at it.</p>
            <p>Though they blaſpheme not in words, yet they may be thought to do ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what in deeds, of much affinity: who
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:121169:15"/>though they allow Children perchance, and ſimple people, in private, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour ſubordinate men; as <hi>Lecturers,</hi> and <hi>Clerks,</hi> in Churches, to uſe the <hi>Lords prayer:</hi> yet themſelves will not do it that honour, as to uſe it in that ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity of words, as delivered and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended unto us by Chriſt, but, either not at all: or ſo <hi>diſlocated,</hi> (which we ſhould not except againſt, if done in <hi>imitation,</hi> and not in <hi>liew</hi> of the <hi>Lords prayer</hi>) and diſmembred with their own cenceptions, that little or nothing of it doth appear in its own ſhape and form.</p>
            <p>Now we are to proceed to the conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of the Text; we will firſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider of a general objection, or evaſion rather, which <hi>I</hi> find ſome have uſed in this very point. We urge the plain literal ſenſe. Yes, but all things (ſay they) in Scripture, are not to be taken litterally. We grant it: but withall we ſay, to make uſe of this objection upon all occaſions, when we find our
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:121169:15"/>ſelves pinched, without any ground at all, of either words, reaſon, circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> is as much as to void all Scripture, and to ſubſtitute our own phanſies and imaginations in lieu of it. The Scripture ſaith. <hi>Thou ſhalt not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip images, Thou ſhalt not commit adultery, Thou ſhalt not kill, ſteal,</hi> &amp;c. Yea, but every thing in the Scripture is not to be taken literally. What then is the uſe of the Scriptures, I would fain know, if it be enough to ſay ſo, when we would not have it to ſay, what croſſes our humors, intereſt, or prejudice? The Reader will give me leave to inſiſt a little upon this point. It will be of good uſe to our preſent occaſion, and he will find it before he come to the end. All things in Scripture are not to be taken literally: No: there be many Types and Figures in the Scriptures; Metaphors and Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlations: many things ſpoken by way of ſimilitude, which muſt not be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood literally; and may eaſily be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, without any other Comment
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:121169:16"/>(or expoſition) than nature and common ſenſe. God ſpeaking unto men, doth condeſcend to ſpeak to them in the lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage of men. When Chriſt ſtyleth the <hi>Phariſees, Generation of Vipers,</hi> can any be ſo ſimple, or ſo malicious, as to make him ſay, that they were really begotten of Vipers? or when he ſaith to his <hi>Diſciples;</hi> that he is the <hi>Vine,</hi> and they the <hi>branches:</hi> that he intended it of a real <hi>Vine</hi> and <hi>Branches?</hi> When the Pſalmiſt calls his God a <hi>Rock:</hi> who would, who could, man, woman or child; (that is come to the age of underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing) argue from thence, that <hi>David</hi> was an Idolator, becauſe he did worſhip ſtones? But here is nothing of that na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; (figurative or metaphorical) in the words we have to do with; we ſhall not need to ſay more.</p>
            <p>Again, Prophecies, are obſcure: it is their nature to be ſo, not many things in them (we grant, ordinarily,) to be taken literally; but we need not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt upon it: here is no thing of that na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture neither.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:121169:16"/>
            <p> Again, Myſterious, ſacramental things are commonly involved in figures: it is their nature to be ſo. That is not a <hi>Sacrament</hi> properly, that doth not ſhew ſomewhat that may be ſeen, whereby it would have ſomewhat underſtood that is not ſeen.</p>
            <p>And do we wonder if Figures be uſed, when they are ſpoken of? Or ſhould we in reaſon preſs the letter in ſuch ſpeeches, even againſt all ſenſe and reaſon? Will any man ſay, that the <hi>Circumciſion</hi> was a <hi>Covenant,</hi> literally, becauſe it is ſo called: or that the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> were in motion, when they did eat the Paſchal Lamb, becauſe it is called the <hi>Paſſeover?</hi> Or that Chriſt, <hi>before he was made fleſh,</hi> was a <hi>Stone,</hi> becauſe St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, Chriſt was the <hi>Rock</hi> that followed the <hi>Iſraelites?</hi> If therefore Chriſt ſaith, the Sacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal <hi>Cup</hi> is the <hi>New Teſtament,</hi> or <hi>Teſtament in his blood,</hi> (as St. <hi>Paul</hi> expreſſeth him) or that the ſacramental bread is his <hi>bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy;</hi> can we be charged with infidelity, becauſe we believe a figure in the words,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:121169:17"/>(the proper ſtyle of <hi>Sacraments</hi>) though in that figure, a <hi>reality,</hi> as to the benefit, as conſiderable to us, as we could ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect from a viſible preſence, or partici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation.</p>
            <p>Again, <hi>St. Austin</hi> hath a rule, and much notice is taken of it: <hi>Si praecepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>va locutio eſt, aut flagitium, aut facinus vetans,</hi> &amp;c. Where we have a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, (ſaith he, or to that effect) that commands nothing againſt civility, or moral honeſty: we muſt take it literally; otherwiſe figuratively. But here is nothing in this queſtion of the <hi>Lords Prayer</hi> that comes within that compaſs, nothing of that nature objected againſt it, (that <hi>I</hi> know of,) or the uſe of it, though the irreverent carriage of ſome men in ſome places) (as <hi>I</hi> have heard) might make ſome men ſuſpect, that they (if otherwiſe ſober and religious) apprehended ſomewhat in it, very offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive to religious ears.</p>
            <p>And now that the Reader may know this is no digreſſion, <hi>I</hi> muſt tell him, <hi>I</hi> find
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:121169:17"/>them, by ſome that have written a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the uſe of the <hi>Lords Prayer,</hi> as a prayer, them, I ſay, that ſtick to the plain literal meaning of Chriſts words in the inſtitution of this holy Prayer, charged with ſome Popery, or imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (at leaſt) of Popery, upon this ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ground, becauſe Papiſts ſtick to the literal ſenſe of theſe ſacramental words, <hi>Hoc eſt corpus meum,</hi> this is my <hi>Body:</hi> I will ſet down their words, <hi>In eo vero quod tantopere urgetis verba ipſa:</hi> Quando oratis, dicite, <hi>Pater noſter,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>quid aliud agitis, quam quod Papiſtae ſolent in quaeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one Sacramenti, urgentes</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>&amp; ad nauſeam uſque objicientes verba illa,</hi> Hoc eſt corpus meum. They are the words of one <hi>Franciſcus Johnſonus,</hi> who had the reputation of a wondrous able man among the Sectaries, (or Puritans) of thoſe times, in anſwer to <hi>John Carpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> a reclaimed Papiſt, a ſon of the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What particular Sect, beſides a Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritan them an was of, I know not. Some
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:121169:18"/>what it ſeems between <hi>Presbytery,</hi> and right down <hi>Anabaptiſm.</hi> For Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm he diſclaims. And Presbyterian Government (at the very laſt of his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe) as well as Epiſcopy, he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounceth to be derived from the Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt. Whether <hi>Independants</hi> were then known, I know not. But let the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dee judge what theſe men would bring Religion, and the word of God unto. If this be Popery, or Popiſh, when there is no imaginable ground, or colour for any other, to ſtick to the literal ſenſe of Scripture: If I ſay to a thief, <hi>steal not;</hi> and tell him, it is forbidden in the Scripture, what a ready evaſion will he have? whileſt I think to convince him by the word of God, he will impeach me (and truly we know many have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally ſuffered for more ridiculous and groundleſs imputations, as the <hi>Surpliſs,</hi> and the like:) of being a Papiſt, or a friend to Papiſts: (to their cauſe I mean; for their perſons we may love and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, as they ſhall merit, I hope, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:121169:18"/>offence:) or perchance of making the <hi>Tranſubstantiation</hi> an article of my faith, becauſe I preſs the literal ſenſe againſt ſtealing. The beſt is, ordinary theft, the Law provides againſt: but <hi>Sacriledge,</hi> both by the Law of God, and by the rules of right reaſon, a greater theft, will eaſily be avoided by this ſophiſtry; and perchance, inſtead of a crime, be made the <hi>Character</hi> of a Saint. As this is, ſo is all the reſt, that I find in that great Champion (as he was accounted in thoſe dayes) of Sectaries, againſt the uſe of the <hi>Lords prayer:</hi> ſuch ridiculous, ſenſeleſs ſophiſtry, as I ſcarce re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member the like, in any thing that ever I read. But in ſuch a caſe, (to prove twice two, not to be four: that the ſnow is black, and the Sun the cauſe of darkneſs:) who can expect it other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe? Yet in this perchance we may commend his ingenuity above ſome others, that he freely confeſſeth the lite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral obvious ſenſe to be of our ſide.</p>
            <p>This prayer then, (or pattern of
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:121169:19"/>prayer if you will) is ſet down, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded in two Goſpels, St. <hi>Matthew</hi> and St. <hi>Luke;</hi> the ſame words (in ſubſtance) in both Goſpels: but as divers have well obſerved, uttered by Chriſt, (and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded accordingly by the Evangeliſts, as ſpoken and preſcribed by him) at two ſeveral times, and upon ſeveral occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: which makes it the more bind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, becauſe twice delivered in the ſame form.</p>
            <p>In St. <hi>Mathew,</hi> Chriſt begins with the Doctrine of praying in general, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſundry precepts and inſtructions, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds to a particular form: <hi>After this manner therefore pray ye, Our Father</hi> &amp;c. which is well obſerved by the <hi>Arabick</hi> tranſlator, exhibited in the late <hi>London Bible,</hi> (that noble, and little leſs than miraculous work, if we conſider all Circumſtances) where we find this di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion; firſt, from <hi>ver.</hi> 5. to <hi>verſe</hi> 9. <hi>Doctrina Orandi, Conſilium de oratione:</hi> then, <hi>Formula Orandi:</hi> an excellent me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod, much neglected in theſe dayes
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:121169:19"/>of <hi>Inſpiration;</hi> when ignorant illiterate creatures are put to it, <hi>illotis manibus:</hi> who though they know little or nothing of Prayer in general, more than this, that they muſt be ſo long, and keep ſaying whatever it be, yet are made believe, (and are ſoon perſwaded) they do it far better, than they, who have long ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>died the duty of prayer in general, and think, it becomes them to conſider of what they ſay, when they are to ſpeak to <hi>Almighty God,</hi> upon any particular oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion.</p>
            <p>Now before we proceed to further exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of the words, it will not be amiſs to take into conſideration, what hath been (ſo far as we can find by books) the opinion of men in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, concerning this duty of prayer.</p>
            <p>In ancienteſt times among Heathens, (that is, men that had the light of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture only to guide them:) it did belong unto Poets, who were the <hi>Theologues,</hi> or
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:121169:20"/>
               <hi>Divines</hi> of the times, to teach men forms of prayer for every Deitie they wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped. Such forms of <hi>Invocations</hi> of <hi>Orpheus,</hi> ſo called; of <hi>Homer,</hi> are yet ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant. The doctrine of prayer was hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by philoſophers; as <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> among others; but that work of his is not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant. But by <hi>Plato</hi> alſo, which is yet extant. In that Treatiſe <hi>Plato</hi> doth much commend a form of prayer, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed by ſome antient poet, not named by him, unknown to us, which <hi>Calvin</hi> in his Inſtitutions, as <hi>I</hi> remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, takes good notice of, and is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited in <hi>Greek</hi> by <hi>Hugo Grotius</hi> in his <hi>Annotations</hi> upon <hi>Mathew.</hi> A very com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable form indeed; the Author and thoſe times conſidered; and which may be ſaid, in ſome reſpects, to come nearer to the <hi>Lords prayer,</hi> than many prayers that are made after that pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern, as is pretended. For <hi>I</hi> take that part of the <hi>Lords prayer,</hi> to be a very conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable part of it, where we are taught to pray, <hi>That the Will of God,</hi> not
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:121169:20"/>out will, <hi>be done:</hi> For ſo I think the words ought to be underſtood, and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed, out of that other exemplary form of prayer, uſed by Chriſt himſelf, and for himſelf, (at that time) parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly, <hi>O my Father, if it be poſsible, let this cup paſs from me, nevertheleſs, not as I will, but as thou wilt,</hi> Mat. 26.39. And again, <hi>verſe</hi> 42. <hi>Thy will be done:</hi> And ſo again, <hi>verſe</hi> 44. Whereas our prayers commonly, inſtead of referring our Wills to Gods Will, are, that our Wills may be done, and that too, with much importunity. Yea ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, we are ready to expoſtulate with God, if we have not what we ask; though God knows, when we have it, we have many times occaſion enough to wiſh, that we had not had our wills; that God had not heard our Prayers. Again, In the <hi>Lords Prayers,</hi> we pray for <hi>our dayly bread:</hi> which are general words, tranſlated by ſome, <hi>panem indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentiae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> noſtrae:</hi> referring particulars to God, who knows better than we, what
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:121169:21"/>is convenient for us, if we durſt truſt him.</p>
            <p>Now that old form commended by <hi>Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to,</hi> was this.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Plato</hi> indeed, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, becauſe of the verb <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> that followeth, as in proſe; but without the verb, that is, as in the verſe, ordinary conſtruction doth require (and ſo it ſhould have been printed in <hi>Hugo Grotius</hi>) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: as it is in the <hi>Anthologie</hi> of Greek ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and elſewhere. Yet an <hi>Infinitive</hi> might have ſtood well enough for an Indicative, if the former verb had been ſo too. But this <hi>obiter:</hi> In latin divers have done them; be content with my tranſlation for this once, to ſave me further labour of ſeeking.</p>
            <q>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:121169:21"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>Quae data</hi>
                  <note place="margin">* That is, things honeſt and juſt, according to the opinion of divers antient Philoſophers, who main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd that nothing was tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly profitable, but what was honeſt and juſt: So <hi>Plato,</hi> ſo divers others. <hi>Tully</hi> in his Offices at large. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was this an Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion in the School, or Academic only for the Exerciſe of their tongues, or wit, (as ſome lately in the Pulpit, <hi>Get faith,</hi> &amp;c. if it be true) but an Opinion maintained and aſſerted by ſome of them in their greateſt tryals; as may appear by thoſe words of <hi>Tully,</hi> when the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-real was invaded by <hi>Caeſar,</hi> and complyance the only way to ſave, or to get Eſtates; he then wrote thus unto his friend, <hi>Quid rectum ſit apparel: quid ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pediat, obſcurum eſt; ita tamen ut ſi nos ii ſamus qui eſſe debemus, id eſt, ſtudio digni, &amp; l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>teris <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>,</hi> (that is, conſtant to our Principles and former Profeſſion) <hi>dubitare non poſſimus, qui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> ea maxime conducant quae ſunt rectiſſima.</hi> What grounds they had for this opinion, that had no certain knowledge of any reward after this life, I know not. Chriſtians have, I am ſure. Let them look to it whom it concerns.</note> 
                  <hi>conducent, vel non orantibus ultro</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Da Pater Alme: preces damnoſas, Alme, negato.</hi>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>As for the ſenſe in Engliſh, though I love a good verſe heartily; yet my ſelf I know, was never born to be a Poet in any Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore never minded it; yet I think it neceſſary to put the words into ſome <hi>Rymes,</hi> that it may be known what they are (ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes) in the Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal.
<note place="margin">†
<q>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Great God, we thee beſeech, thoſe good things us to grant,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Asked, or unasked; thy ſelf doth know we want.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>As for thoſe things we ask; if ſuch as in the end</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Hurtfull (thou know'ſt) will prove; from ſuch, great God, defend.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </q>
               </note>
            </p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:121169:22"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Juvenal</hi> the Poet, hath a whole Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyre of this Subject, of the ignorance of man, in point of praying. <hi>Perſius,</hi> another; both inſiſt upon many parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars, to ſhew the danger of raſh, haſty prayers. In the Old Teſtament, there be many preſcript forms of prayers, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to beſt Interpreters. <hi>Davids</hi>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:121169:22"/>Pſalms in general were uſed, (and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly intended many of them from the very beginning) moſt of them by the ancient Jews, before Chriſts time, to that purpoſe. But more of this by and by.</p>
            <p>In point of reaſon therefore, ſince prayer hath alwayes been a matter of ſuch difficulty and danger withal; and that preſcript forms have been uſed, not among Heathens only, but <hi>Iſraelites</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, who would not think it moſt proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that when Chriſt ſaid, (as his words are recorded by St. <hi>Mathew,</hi> verſe 9.) <hi>After this manner therefore pray ye, Our Father,</hi> &amp;c. He intended a preſcript form? Or if he had not intended it ſo, yet the words in ordinary conſtruction, importing ſo much, he would have uſed ſome words to prevent our mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake? Some fly to the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> here, and tell us, it importeth ſometimes no more, than a reſemblance or likeneſs. We grant it. But what word is there almoſt to be found, or can be uſed by
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:121169:23"/>any man or Author, but is ſometimes taken in a different ſenſe? The que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion is, whether any ground for any ſuch ſenſe in this place; ſuch ſenſe, I mean, as ſhould exclude the more uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al and ordinary. No man I think will deny, but that in ordinary conſtruction, when it is ſaid, you ſhall ſay thus; The words that follow there, are intended, and no other. As when God in <hi>Exo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus</hi> often ſaith unto <hi>Moſes, Go, and ſay unto</hi> Pharaoh, <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord God of Iſrael,</hi> that thoſe very words there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded, were uſed by God unto <hi>Moſes,</hi> when he gave him his commiſſion. And <hi>Gen.</hi> 45.9. <hi>Thus ſaith thy ſon</hi> Joſeph, &amp;c. It followeth, <hi>verſe</hi> 27. <hi>And they told him all the words of</hi> Joſeph, <hi>which he had ſaid unto them.</hi> Infinite places of Scripture might be produced: ſome, where the very ſame words are repeat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; but that I think it will be granted by all men, that as there is a <hi>Thus</hi> of ſimilitude, which we deny not; ſo of <hi>Identity;</hi> which by the due conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:121169:23"/>of circumſtances, and coherence, is generally to be determined.</p>
            <p>It is well obſerved by ſome, that have written of this Subject, that had Chriſt intended a meer model of prayer by thoſe words, he would rather (in all probabilitie, were it but to prevent our error) have ſaid, pray that your ſins may be forgiven you, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as elſewhere, <hi>pray that your flight may be in the ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, Though I know the word <hi>Amen,</hi> is uſed, not at the beginning on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but at the end alſo of ſome ſpeeches, that are not prayers properly: yet it will not be denyed, that it is moſt proper at the end to formal prayers: witneſs St. <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.15, 16. ſo that even from this word may be be collected ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what, which alone would be of no great weight perchance; but joyned with ſo much evidence, and other ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary conſequence, is not imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent.</p>
            <p>Now were it ſo that this prayer, and
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:121169:24"/>Chriſts words about it, had been regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred by St. <hi>Mathew</hi> only, I think no more could rationally be required, to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade men that are not apt to be ſway<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by ſomewhat elſe more ſtrongly than reaſon. There be many other truths delivered, with leſs evidence of truth, which we generally imbrace, both in the Old and New Teſtament. As on the other ſide, we muſt confeſs by ſad experience, that no Truth can be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered with ſo much evidence, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtation of words and circumſtances, but private Intereſt, partiality, faction, prejudice, and the like, may draw to a contrary ſenſe: ſo that if men cannot perſwade themſelves (though no wonder, if they do, even they that otherwiſe are judicions enough: ſtrong intereſt, if men once give way, and be worldly given, will blind beſt Judgements in time) and their conſciences, that it is ſo: yet they will hope by cunning and ſophiſtry, they ſhall be able to perſwade others. But Gods providence in this particular, hath
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:121169:24"/>otherwiſe ordered it. For as if St. <hi>Luke</hi> had fore-ſeen (by the Spirit) a poſſibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty that ſome would, or might ſtick at, and draw Arguments from the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in St. <hi>Mathew:</hi> he hath uſed ſuch words, as every man muſt confeſs, leave no ground at all for ſcruples (though ſought and deſired) and evaſions; except we fly to figures and metaphors, of which ſomewhat hath been ſaid before.</p>
            <p>But before we ſet down the very words, we muſt take notice of ſome circumſtances of ſtory belonging to this buſineſs, which St. <hi>Luke</hi> doth here ſet down. Firſt, That Chriſt had been praying, when the Diſciples did peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion him, that he would teach them to pray. Prayer is a duty that Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf was much converſant in: we find that by many places: yet it is obſerved by ſome, we do not find expreſſed any where, that Chriſt prayed with his Diſciples (ordinary common prayers excepted) but alwayes by himſelf. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers add, nor in the Temple publickly.
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:121169:25"/>How the obſervation will hold, will not much concern. If his Diſciples hath heard him often, there was good ground for their requeſt, that when they ſhould not have the comfort of his prayers by bodily preſence; yet they might not want the comfort of praying in his own words, when himſelf ſhould be out of ſight; ſuch words as they might pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume (with the concurrence of a pure and well prepared heart) ſhould al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes be moſt acceptable, as to Him, from whom they had received them; ſo to Him, that had ſent him with a promiſe to hear petitions in his Name: very likely therefore (they might think) to like them beſt that ſhould come with a double ſtamp both of his words and name. But if they did not often pray with him, when he uſed other prayers than thoſe that were known and ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary (of which we ſhall ſay more by and by) the leſs they had been acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with his practiſe in that kind, from which they might frame a pattern to
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:121169:25"/>themſelves: the more reaſon they had to require of him a certain form, which might ſupply their want.</p>
            <p>But ſecondly, the Diſciples ground their petition upon St. <hi>Johns</hi> example, <hi>Lord teach us to pray, as John taught his Diſciples.</hi> Now I think it is not doubted by any man, or Interpreter of Scripture, but that <hi>John</hi> delivered unto his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples a formal prayer. Had St. <hi>John</hi> on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly delivered unto them a pattern to frame their prayers by, I doubt they would have been much unſatisfied. It requireth no little skill or judgement, to follow a pattern well. It is not likely <hi>John</hi> Baptiſt his Diſciples were ſuch rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy men all, that he would truſt them with a bare pattern. And whereas it is very probable (I am not alone that think ſo) that St. <hi>John</hi>'s Diſciples were, if not known and diſcerned from others abroad (as the <hi>Pythagoreans</hi> by their <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>:) yet much united and faſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed among themſelves, by this prayer their Maſter had taught them: had
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:121169:26"/>it been a bare pattern, they might have jarred even unto Sects, and factions for all that: as we ſee all Chriſtians do not pray after one ſort, who pretend all to follow the ſame pattern.</p>
            <p>This may be further confirmed by the conſideration of what was uſual among the <hi>Jews.</hi> Now ſo it is, (it cannot be denyed, but by them that are paſt ſhame, who to advantage that cauſe, whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it is, to which their Intereſt hath wedded them, will adventure upon any thing) that the <hi>Jewes,</hi> time out of mind, had been uſed to ſet forms of prayer. That they uſed no other in private, and upon extraordinary occaſions, no man I think ever ſaid: but that in their ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn devotions, and moſt publick oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions they did uſe ſet forms, all Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſtants and Papiſts (as many as I have ſeen, or at this time remember) are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting. Firſt of <hi>Numb.</hi> 23.4, 6. who can doubt, but the words contain a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcript form of <hi>Bleſsing, [In this wiſe,</hi> or <hi>in this ſet forme of words</hi>] the Anno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:121169:26"/>there. But it is one thing to bleſs, another to pray, ſay ſome. Indeed a man may pray, and neither bleſs nor curſe, that is certain: but to ſay, that bleſſing may not be the Subject of a prayer, either publick or private, as well as any thing elſe, is as ridiculous, as it is apparent, that this bleſſing here preſcribed, is a very formal prayer. The Text is as clear, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 29, 30. <hi>Heze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiah the King, and the Princes commanded the Levites to ſing praiſe unto the Lord, with the words of David, and Aſaph the Seer.</hi> And 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 16. the Pſalmes (or pſalme, as there joyned) ſtand up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Record, that were appointed by <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> and particularly <hi>verſe</hi> 35. <hi>And ſay yea, &amp;c.</hi> the Annotations there: [It is a phraſe of incitation, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> or, it is a direction to uſe this form, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 14.2. <hi>Duke</hi> 11.2.] The latter Quotation, <hi>Luke</hi> 11.2. referring to theſe very words and ſubject we are now upon. <hi>Pſalm</hi> the 20. is a form of prayer, or inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion, as the pſalm following of Thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:121169:27"/>as moſt Interpreters do agree. Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers others pſalmes there be intended for ſet forms, upon ſeveral occaſions, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved by moſt Interpreters. <hi>Ainſworth</hi> upon the 24. pſalm, out of a paſſage of <hi>Maimonides,</hi> ſhews what pſalm was ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for every day of the weeke, at the time of Divine ſervice, long before Chriſt: and ſome of thoſe pſalms, I am ſure, though commonly called <hi>pſalms</hi> or <hi>ſongs;</hi> are prayers and interceſſions, and nothing elſe; as particularly, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 94. Others tell us of whole <hi>Liturgies,</hi> (or <hi>publick ſervice-books</hi>) of thoſe dayes yet extant, in part: after which I ſhall not need to make further enquiry at this time, becauſe I think I have ſaid enough to this purpoſe; and no more, I think, but will eaſily be granted.</p>
            <p>It was proper enough, I think, to take notice of thoſe things, obſerved by St. <hi>Luke</hi> certainly, for their further ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, (in this very point) that ſhould need it. But now we are come to the words themſelves, I would deſire the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:121169:27"/>Reader, for a while to forget all that hath been ſaid hitherto, (but withal, to lay aſide, if it were poſſible, all prejudice and partiality) and when he hath read the words in St. <hi>Luke, (And he ſaid unto them, When ye pray, ſay, Our Father,</hi> &amp;c.) to conſider with himſelf, whether he think any thing wanting to them, to make them plain, and expreſs enough. I will ſay more; let it be grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, (for a while at leaſt) that Chriſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended thoſe words, as a form of prayer to be uſed by his Diſciples, and by conſequent, by ſuch as ſhould pretend to him in after-ages: I would have the Reader to pauſe and conſider with himſelf, what words more expreſs, more pregnant and ſignificant, could be uſed to that purpoſe, to prevent all doubts and evaſions. The words them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves run in the form of a prayer, that, no man doth deny: and therefore a man would think, had there been no more in the Text, but; <hi>And he ſaid, Our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> &amp;c. his intention had been plain enough, <hi>You ſhall pray thus:</hi> that is not
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:121169:28"/>more expreſs, but more binding. But <hi>when you pray,</hi> ſay: for my part, I muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, what words could have been uſed more expreſs, or more binding, I can think of none. I deny not, but Chriſt might have uſed more words. He might have ſaid, had he pleaſed, or thought fit: You ſhall have your deſire: I will teach you, what you ſhall ſay. You ſhall have a form of prayer from me, which you may uſe: nay, what you made your requeſt, I ſhall lay upon you, and all Chriſtians of all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, as a duty: <hi>When ye pray,</hi> ſay: In your beſt devotions, though you uſe other prayers, as your particular occaſions ſhall require; yet uſe this, as your beſt prayer, <hi>Our Father,</hi> &amp;c. He might have ſaid, I know the time will come, when men out of an high conceit of their own parts, and in oppoſition to others, whom they ſhall uſe, or have uſed ſo and ſo, will not allow theſe words to be preſcribed by me as a form of prayer, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Some ſuch words, I grant, might have been ſpoken: but as there
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:121169:28"/>is no part of Scripture ſo clear or ſo ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally received, but may be abuſed, quarrelled, denyed; ſo is there as lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle reaſon for any ſuch words in this, as in any other place, that hath afford<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed matter of ſtrife, and contention in any age of the world.</p>
            <p>After ſuch evidence of Scripture, that is, of the word of God: the conſent or authority of man may be thought ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluous. And what if all men, all Chriſtians that have been hitherto, in all places, in all ages of the world, had not all been of one opinion about it, would not, ſhould not, the greateſt part have ſerved? would it not have become men, that pretend to honour the Scripture ſo much, as the <hi>Word of God;</hi> and to be ſuch enemies to them that diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour it; have become them, I ſay, where the Text is ſo clear and expreſs, to have adhered unto it, even againſt the conſent of the major part? Should we believe nothing as Chriſtians, but what is cleerly declared in Scripture,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:121169:29"/>&amp; may be ſaid to have been aſſented unto by Chriſtians, in all ages, and places without any contradiction or oppoſition: I doubt our faith would be much abridg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. But we muſt be as good as our undertaking. If we have not general conſent of former and latter ages, (ſo far as can be found out by Hiſtory: thoſe new men of the late <hi>reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> excepted) evidence of Scripture ſhall be no good plea for us; will for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit our cauſe.</p>
            <p>Some it may be will here expect, that we ſhould begin to ſearch into ancient Records and Monuments for the opinion and practice of the ancient Chriſtians, and primitive times of the Church: which with all that are not blinded by faction and ſelf-love, muſt needs be of great Authority. But others with more reaſon would think, <hi>I</hi> might better have ſpared this labour, ſince I have to do with men, who as either ſufficiently convicted of the truth of our plea, in this particular; or becauſe they think
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:121169:29"/>it not worth the while (truſting to their own pretended illumination) to take the pains to enquire further into it, will ſooner yield to us the matter of fact, then contend about it; and only except againſt the validity of the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, or authority, alledging for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, that whether it be ſo or no, they do not think themſelves bound to follow them. If you ask them the reaſon, they will tell you, becauſe they were but men, and might err. Let the Reader remember, that the expreſs letter of the Word of God, was yielded unto us before: and now we are to come to the conſent or authority of men, we are told, that men are but men, not Gods. But we go on. They were but men, they ſay; truly I ſay ſo too, they were but men, not Gods; but, <hi>men</hi> that lived ſo many ages nearer to the ſource and ſpring of that infallible authority then familiarly converſant, (we ſpeak now of the ancienteſt, or primitive Chriſtians:) and reſident among men.
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:121169:30"/>
               <hi>Men,</hi> who generally forſook all things that are deareſt unto men uſually, (for which things many in this age, make nothing to forſake their former faith:) to adhere unto Chriſt: <hi>Men,</hi> by whoſe holineſs of life, and intolerable (to fleſh and blood) ſufferings for Chriſt, more than by their preaching, whole kingdomes and Nations of Pagans and Infidels were gained to the faith of Chriſt: and why the conſent of ſuch, ſo many, in ſeveral ages; in different places of the world, ſhould not be more conſiderable: but I will proceed no further in the compariſon. Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly, if any man (not engag'd by worldly intereſts) can be ſo ſimple, as not, of himſelf, to be ſenſible; I will not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect that any reaſoning can reſtore him. And why ſhould it be a wonder to a rational man, that ſome are ſo ſimple among Chriſtians, who knows that na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural <hi>fools</hi> and <hi>Idiots,</hi> are little leſs than worſhipped by the Turks (the great Conquerors of the world) for no other
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:121169:30"/>reſpect, but becauſe <hi>fools</hi> and <hi>Idiots?</hi> We therefore take it for granted, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till we know of any that oppoſe it; that we have (beſides cleer Scripture; <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſum &amp; conſuetudinem,</hi> the general conſent and practiſe of one thouſand and five hundred, or ſix hundred years on our ſide. But it will not be amiſs, to ſet down ſome of their words for the better ſatisfaction of the Reader. <hi>Ultimò, ſequitur tritum illud vestrum &amp; Papiſticum argumentum</hi> (ſaith <hi>Johnſon</hi> before named) <hi>de conſuetudine mille quingentorum anno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum.</hi> (Let the Reader take notice, that he calls this preſcription of 1500 years, <hi>arpopiſh argument,</hi> whereby he doth yield to Papiſts, much more than I would, or can: I know nothing among them truly popiſh, that can preſcribe to ſo much antiquity) <hi>De quo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>etiam ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stat, quod vos pro conceſſo ſumitis, hoc tamen ſemper tenendum, vocem Dei in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tura eſſe regulam ſidei,</hi> &amp;c. He doth not ſay, it is altogether ſo, but whether ſo, or no, (for he brings nothing to diſprove
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:121169:31"/>it:) his evaſion is, conſent of many men or ages, is nothing, becauſe the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture only is our rule. And again, a little after, <hi>Poſtrema tua ratio petita eſt ab authoritate Patrum, ut vocantur, quos certum in multis erraſſe,</hi> &amp;c. Here we have the conſent of the Fathers yielded to us. We would commend their mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty for yielding to the truth ſo far; if at the ſame time, they did not more immodeſtly oppoſe their own judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to the acknowledged conſent and authority of ſo many ages; and ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, much better men, than themſelves can pretend unto.</p>
            <p>So from former times, we come now to latter, or preſent. We will not mention the Papiſts, (ſo called) though no man can deny, but there be among them, men of great learning, and I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, religious: but becauſe there is no queſtion of their conſent, and their authority not ſo much ſtood upon by them we have to do with: therefore needleſs here, as I imagine. As for <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:121169:31"/>Divines,</hi> or others, I think we need not ſearch into the writings of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular men, and trouble the Reader with multitude of quotations, which every body that can read, and hath acceſs to books, may eaſily ſtore him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf with, if he will: the practiſe of all <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Churches in all places of <hi>Europe,</hi> (I can give no account of <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependent Conventicles</hi>) which may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear by different <hi>Formularies</hi> and <hi>Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gies</hi> by them ſet out, as the beſt evidence of their opinions generally, ſo I ſuppoſe will give beſt ſatisfaction: ſo that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though ſome particular acknowledged <hi>Protestant</hi> Writer ſhould be found to be of another mind, yet it can be no prejudice to what we have ſaid of their general conſent. Now for their <hi>Formularies,</hi> in a buſineſs ſo expoſed to every mans ſcrutiny, that will take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny paines to ſatisfie himſelf: I ſhall not uſe many words: I have ſome, have had, and ſeen many more, in ſeveral languages: never yet lighted upon any,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:121169:32"/>in which <hi>the Lords Prayer</hi> was not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed, to be uſed by Preiſts and people in expreſſe termes, as in the Goſpel. So upon confidence, that this alſo will be granted unto us, I ſhall forbeare fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther labour. As for particular authors: though I ſaid before, we cannot un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake for, nor are indeed bound to take notice of every particular man: yet I may truly ſay, no ſuch is known unto me, either by any reading in former times, or by any quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, that I have met with in others upon this occaſion. <hi>Calvin</hi> ſaith of it in his <hi>Inſtitutions,</hi> as much as I would de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, and ſo in his <hi>Harmony:</hi> but that he hath an expreſſion, which might be won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered at: <hi>(non jubet nos conceptis verbis uti)</hi> had he not preſently after explained himſelf, by a more full expreſſion, <hi>ut nuper dixi,</hi> &amp;c. They do him great wrong therefore, that would perſwade us otherwiſe of him, taking the advantage of ſome particular words when his mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing both by his practiſe (witneſſe thoſe <hi>Formularies</hi> ſet out in his time, printed at
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:121169:32"/>
               <hi>Geneva</hi>) and by his writings is ſo eaſily known. Neither ought we to wonder, if nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Calvin,</hi> or any other, whilſt they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend unto us <hi>the Lords Prayer,</hi> be careful, at the ſame time, to prevent, that their words might not be drawn to a wrong ſenſe, as though they commended it as the only prayer to be uſed either publikely, or privatly: which would be a great and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous miſtake: but of that more afterward. I have mentioned <hi>Luther</hi> ſomewhere, as a great admirer of this holy Prayer. It ſhall not be amiſs therefore to ſet down ſome of his words. In his <hi>Enchiridium piarum pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cationum,</hi> which I have by it ſelf, in a hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome forme: but in his workes alſo, in the <hi>Wittenburg. edit.</hi> (A. D. 1558) to be found: he ſaith; <hi>Sum autem plane certus, Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anum ſatis abunde oraſſe, ſi Orationem Dominicam, vere ac rectè oret: quocun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que id tempore, &amp; quamcunque ejus volet partem. Ne que enim ſi multum verborum numeres, ideo bona est oratio: quod Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus quoque teſtatur,</hi> Math. 6. <hi>Sed ſi crebrò, ac cum magno ardore ad Deum ſuſpires.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And again in the ſame book: <hi>Ubi ad
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:121169:33"/>verbum totam Orationem Dominicam re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citavi, partem unam, aut plures, ſi libet, repeto,</hi> &amp;c. and concludes: <hi>Hic meus eſt orandi mos, et ratio. Nam quotidie ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>huc Orationem hanc Dominicam, quodam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modo ſugo, uti infantulus: bibo, &amp; mando, uti adultus; nec tamen ea ſatiari poſſum. Atque etiam dulcior &amp; gratior mihi eſt ipſis Pſalmis, quibus tamen mirificè &amp; unice delector: quos &amp; maximi facio. Profectò res ipſa clamat, à ſummo &amp; praeſtantiſsimo artifice, eam orationem eſſe compoſitam, &amp; praeformatam.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In another Treatiſe he ſaith: <hi>Cum haec Oratio à Chriſto habeat originem, debet indubitanter eminentiſsima, nobiliſsima, optimaque cenſeri: quâ ſi meliorem ſciviſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet integerrimus ac fideliſsimus magister, eam quoque nos ille docuiſſet.</hi> I will not undertake for the exactneſs or propriety of the expreſſion, (in thoſe words, <hi>ſi meliorem ſciviſſet</hi>) which the vehemency of his admiration and affection ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſted unto him. It would make a man ſuſpect, that even in thoſe dayes, he had met with ſome that thought, they
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:121169:33"/>could pray as well, if not better, and perchance under pretence of imitation, would have been content (if they might) to leave it out of their publike devotions. But I do but ſuſpect. It is apparent, he was a great admirer of it, and had very great zeale to it; and for it. <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi>'s zeale to this prayer, puts me in minde of <hi>Ludovicus Vives,</hi> a Papiſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, not a Proteſtant, but generally acknowledged a learned, wiſe, devout man: he hath written a <hi>Commentary,</hi> as he calls it, upon the <hi>Lords prayer.</hi> How zealouſly he was affected towards it, and how much he had it in admiration, his <hi>preface</hi> will ſhew; it is well worth the reading. But of Proteſtant Divines, I make no queſtion, but a man might make a whole book, that ſhould collect their ſeveral Elogies, and teſtimonies concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this Prayer, as it is <hi>a forme of prayer;</hi> but that it is not our buſineſs here. Generall conſent is the thing that we contend for, and upon which we have in part ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed our caſe, in the ſtating of it. And
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:121169:34"/>for that we have appealed to the <hi>Formu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laries,</hi> that are extant of moſt Proteſtant Churches beyond the ſeas: which is the moſt direct and pertinent proof, that any man can expect. And if we knew any thing objected by any body in oppoſition to what we mantaine, we would take notice of it. <hi>I</hi> find no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of that nature in <hi>Johnſon,</hi> before ſpoken of, though <hi>Carpenter</hi> had not omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted it, but put it to him in direct termes. <hi>Nullane Proteſtantium Eccleſia praeter ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtram Synagogulam oculos habuit, aut men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem? An vos ſoli ſapitis,</hi> &amp;c. (in St. <hi>Auguſtin</hi>'s words againſt <hi>Donatus</hi>) to which particular I finde no anſwer at all, though the <hi>anſwer,</hi> (as called) be large and tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in general beyond meaſure. It ſeemes therefore he could not deny it, but all Proteſtant Churches were of another mind. If he had known any, certainly we ſhould have heard of it. What notice therefore I have taken of particular men, as <hi>Luther</hi> and <hi>Calvin;</hi> is over and above, becauſe of their eminency: <hi>Perkins</hi> in
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:121169:34"/>England, his authority would once have gone a great way, with thoſe men eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, that pretended to more than ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary ſtrictneſſe in religion. What his opinion was in this matter, ſhall be ſeen at the end, where we take notice of ſome ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections.</p>
            <p>But now ſince we have named ſome particular men, and have ſeen what de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion they had (<hi>Luther</hi> eſpecially) to this holy Prayer: with what zeale, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration they ſpeak of it: let it not paſſe without ſome further obſervation. I make no queſtion, but the like may be ſaid, and obſerved of divers others emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently pious and learned in all ages. I have heard of ſome particularly in our age; men of great fame, that have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed to receive ſingular comfort of it, which might alſo be gathered by their frequent uſe of it in time of ſickneſſe. Now I would gladly know of thoſe men (and I wiſh they would take it into their ſerions conſideration) of thoſe men, I ſay, who not only forbeare the uſe of
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:121169:35"/>it themſelves, but alſo forbid it to others; and when uſed in their preſence, have ſhewed much trouble and indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as it is reported of ſome and may be true, for ought I know, of many more: whether it be likely, or poſſible, that ſuch averſeneſs and antipathy in them: ſuch zeale and devotion in others, whom themſelves perchance will not deny to have been pious and religious; ſhould pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from one and the ſame ſpirit. And if they cannot find in their hearts to ſay, or to thinck, that it was a ſpirit of illuſion, that led thoſe good and godly men unto ſuch eſteeme and admiration of this prayer: from what ſpirit can their antipathy proceed? For my part (and I doubt not but it is the mind of many thouſand Chriſtians in England beſides) though I know my ſelf too great a ſinner to expect that God ſhould afford me thoſe extraordinary raviſhing content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and delights of the ſoule, which I believe he hath done, and doth unto many, more deſerving; in the uſe of
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:121169:35"/>this holy prayer: Yet I ſhould be very ſorry, it ſhould be in the power of any man living, to bereave me of that right and priviledge I have, as a Chriſtian, unto it, and the uſe of it, whileſt I live: and I ſhall ever believe, that a reverent uſe, and high eſteem of it, as immediately proceeding from, and commended un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us by ſuch a ONE, to whom all manner of adoration is due; is no ſmall part of that worſhip we owe unto God.</p>
            <p>All things that have been ſaid hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to well conſidered, it may perchance make ſome wonder in ſome, what ſhould induce men; ſome, learned, and conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious otherwiſe; (as it is to be hoped:) but however, men, that profeſſe Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; to be ſo ſet againſt this prayer, that beareth the name of the <hi>Lord and Saviour of men:</hi> and I remember an obſervation in <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> that, to give full ſatisfaction in a doubtful buſines, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, &amp;c. We ſhould not only <hi>tell what is truth, but alſo take paines to diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:121169:36"/>the ground of the error, or that which is falſe.</hi> Firſt then it muſt be granted, that even before theſe times, there were ſome in the world, that begun to hatch this monſter: but being but few and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderable, ſtanding divided from all the <hi>Reformed Churches</hi> in Europ; it leaves a wonder ſtill, their opinion ſhould be embraced by men accounted ſober, and making profeſſion of the <hi>proteſtant Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> We ſay therefore in the ſecond place, that the ſpirit of <hi>Enthaſiuſme,</hi> ſince the reines of order and diſcipline have been looſe, and all liberty left unto men (<hi>Papiſts</hi> and <hi>Prelaticall,</hi> for ſo it pleaſeth them to joyne us, only excepted) to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low their own fancies in all things belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Gods worſhip; having much pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed (as it hath done in ſome ages of the world before this) among us, men have been very prone, to think them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves inſpired in the uſe of their extemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orary faculty, which formerly (and it may be, formerly too much neglected) they had not been ſo well acquainted
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:121169:36"/>with: and through ignorance of <hi>Nature,</hi> and former times, (as hath been declared, and proved at large elſewhere<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>) did apprehend a ſupernatural cauſe, where in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed there was no cauſe at all: and this probably might make them by degrees, to loath and contemn this <hi>holy prayer.</hi> A third reaſon may be, the violence of op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as St. <hi>Baſil</hi> called it; Prelatical men having been uſed as they have been, put out of all, ſilenced, made incapable &amp;c. it was very conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent, their cauſe ſhould be made as odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, as art and invention could make it.</p>
            <p>God forbid I ſhould take upon me to excuſe any thing that hath been amiſſe. If I did not believe of myſelfe, there was ſomewhat of that kind (in Church, or Commonwealth, or both:) yet the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God (whom I believe to be moſt juſt) ſo great, and ſo heavy, would make me think ſo. But, why ſo many things formerly practiſed and obſerved in the Church of England, as for example; <hi>publike Catechiſing,</hi> ſo neceſſary to up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:121169:37"/>Chriſtianity among men, though not ſo pleaſing to itching eares, as ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary preaching is: <hi>the uſe of the Sacraments,</hi> which in divers Pariſhes, where formerly duly adminiſtred, are now ſcarce known, or named: the <hi>obſervation of ſome prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall holydayes,</hi> as the anniverſary com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memoration of the birth of Chriſt, of his Reſurrection <hi>&amp;c.</hi> by which (though abuſed by profane men, as all things may be) the faith of moſt was much confirmed, honour and homage, in the moſt ſolemne manner, done unto Chriſt; not to mention ſome more private things; as <hi>childrens dayly asking their Parents bleſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> upon their knees, (a cuſtome, though not elſewhere obſerved, that I know of; yet much commended by many ſtrangers, that have ſeen the practiſe of it in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, as I can witneſs:) and the like; and among the reſt, the reverent uſe of this <hi>holy prayer:</hi> why theſe I ſay, and the like ſhould be ſo neglected, diſcountenanced, and, (in ſome places, at leaſt) in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner abrogated, having oftentimes thought
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:121169:37"/>of it with grief, I can give my ſelf no reaſon more ſatisfactory to my wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, than that it is done in oppoſition to the former Clergy, becauſe by them re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligiouſly obſerved: Such is the nature of oppoſition; eſpecially where private intereſt doth oblige. But yet, after all this, as to this particular of the <hi>Lords Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er:</hi> to ſpeak my mind freely: I look upon it, rather as a <hi>judgement,</hi> than an <hi>er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror:</hi> or if an <hi>error,</hi> yet as the puniſhment of another: this, juſtly inflicted for ſomewhat, that was more willfull and arbitrary. Let their own conſciences tell them (profeſt Miniſters, or Clergy men I mean; I have nothing to do with others) whether they have not, ſomewhat againſt conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence for politick ends, fiercely oppoſed (I will not ſay perſecuted) ſomewhat, (once, the glory of the Engliſh Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation) which though it pretend not to Divine authority, yet may pretend to the beſt of things eſtabliſhed by humane, among men. And, what if the more oppoſed, becauſe this very prayer
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:121169:38"/>is part of it, too great a part of it, as they pretend? May not we think there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that this hath happened to them, as a judgement, <hi>that their follie might be made manifeſt?</hi> But I will not be too bold upon ſecret judgements: though I have their example, if that would acquit me before God. Sure I am, and I think I may boldly ſpeake it; thoſe Chriſtians have much to anſwer for, who upon ſo little ground of reaſon, and againſt ſuch manifeſt Scripture, could ſo eaſily be drawn away from that piety, which they were bred unto, and in a manner, ſuckt from their mothers breſt; by the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, or perſwaſion of ſuch leaders. But thus it is (and no wonder) when a people is once come to that, as to reduce, (with thoſe falſe Iſraelites, the Prophet <hi>Ezekiel</hi> deſcribes <hi>chap.</hi> 33. <hi>v.</hi> 31, 32.) all religion to the pleaſure of the eare. And for them that are ſuch, for ought I ſee, let them but have what they affect, they may quickly be brought to ſwallow any thing, be it the groſſeſt point of Popery; and
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:121169:38"/>yet think themſelves very religious; yea, (if their Preachers tell them ſo) good Proteſtants.</p>
            <p>There ſeems nothing to remain, but ſome objections to be taken notice of. But I would omit no means untried. Some things, though more remote in ſight, may ſometimes work more with ſome, than more concluding proofs, <hi>Et quae non proſunt ſingula, multa juvant.</hi> This Prayer is commonly called, <hi>The Lords Prayer,</hi> and there is reaſon for it; &amp; there's a day call'd, the <hi>Lords day,</hi> (more properly ſo, than <hi>The Sabbath:</hi>) we will ſee what we may draw from this common appellation, or denomination from the ſame Lord. Our beginning may be thought ſomewhat remote. They that are more quick, will ſoon perceive, what we drive at. Others, I deſire them to have patience, and to read to the end, before they judge.</p>
            <p>I do not know any thing, whereby a man may ſooner and ſurer find him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, whether he be a true Chriſtian indeed, a true Convert, or believer:
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:121169:39"/>then by the generality or ſimplicity (right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, underſtood)of his obedience, and conformity to the Laws and Commands of Chriſt. I will not go to the Planets or Climates, to fetch a reaſon. I will not believe, (though the Patrons of Aſtrologie, do not ſtick to ſay it) that any man is born, either a Murderer or an Adulterer. But ſure it is, that all men are not born by their natural complexion, with equal advantage or diſadvantage, to either vertue or vice. Some have none, or few notable vices: not ſo much, or perchance not at all, out of any love or knowledge of goodneſs, but becauſe they find no inclination to be evil. They love, every body: are not malicious perchance, not revengefull; it is their nature, not religion. Humble, quiet, temperate in all things: it is their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. We may ſay of them, as <hi>Sene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca</hi> of thoſe of the Golden age, <hi>Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantiâ rerum, innocentes erant. Multum autem intereſt, utrum peccare aliquis nolit, aut neſciat.</hi> Some of theſe natural In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocents
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:121169:39"/>(as to the world, and the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick) it may be, there are yet in the world, men and women, in ſome places. We are bound in the judgement of Charity, to account them vertuous, to honour and admire them as ſuch, becauſe we ſee their works: we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not judge of their hearts. But if they have no other motive to goodneſs than nature, or cuſtome, or education; I know not how far it may acquit them from worſe: I am very confident it will never bring them to heaven. So far, wiſe Heathens have gone, who plainly teach and determine, that without <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, (reference to God) no man is truly ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous or innocent, though he may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear ſo outwardly by his actions. So the wiſer Heathens; others, in ſtead of God, they ſay, <hi>Reaſon; non eſt virtus, cui non conſtat ratio,</hi> diſputed at large by <hi>Seneca,</hi> and others. But thoſe ſo generally innocent (in ſight) by nature; I doubt they are not many, except they be innocents indeed, in another ſenſe.
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:121169:40"/>Moſt men are of a mixt temper, as to vice, ſo to ſome vertue. Some men are not given to women: though there were no Laws to bind them, one wife doth ſerve their turn very well: Chaſtity is their vertue. It may be, as little ſubject to Wine: they look upon all exceſs in that kind, as the effects of brutiſh ſenſuality. But then for malice, or envy, or pride, perchance covetouſneſs (which all good natured men, as we call them, do much about) theſe, all, or ſome of them, are ſo natural unto them, that though they are told what they are, and known for ſuch, by all that know them; yet them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves know it not; and though per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chance they do not care to have many like themſelves, yet they will ſooner believe them fools and Idiots that are not, than be perſwaded out of their humour: it is ſo natural and pleaſing. That man, that is all vice, without any natural propenſity to ſome vertue, is not a bad, or vicious man properly, but a Monſter: and ſo indeed ſet out by
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:121169:40"/>the Satyrick, <hi>Monſtrum nulla virtute redemptum A vitiis:</hi> and, <hi>Illaudatus</hi> in the beſt of Poets, (very ſignificantly) a man <hi>that could be commended for nothing;</hi> when he intended (as antient Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marians well obſerve) the worſt of men, a Monſter, ſuch a one as <hi>Buſiris</hi> was, of whom it is ſpoken. I cannot tell, how eaſie generally; but certainly the way to heaven would be much eaſier, might we but take a liberty, to what is moſt natural unto us, and yet be good Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians. He that is vertuous indeed, that is, for God and conſcience-ſake, is, though not equally inclined by nature, yet equally reſolved in his mind, to whatſoever is either commanded, or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden by God in his Word. If he be vicious in ſome kind (as who not?) more than another, it is not becauſe he thinks better of his vice, or for want of ſtriving againſt it: but becauſe as yet he hath not, (to his great grief and ſorrow) been able to maſter his nature: and it may be, long ſtriving, if ſincere
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:121169:41"/>and real, may prove at laſt, through Gods Mercy, to his advantage. This, I think, is a very ſure way, for every man to examine himſelf. And this is the way that St. <hi>Paul</hi> went to convince the Jewes, in a place. The Jewes in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> time were no idolators. They had been in former ages: they were now free from that ſin: it is not laid to their charge no where in the New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament. St. <hi>Jerome</hi> obſerves it very particularly, and ſome others alſo. They extreamly abhorred all other Nations of the world upon that ſcore, and deem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them altogether unworthy of Gods mercy. St. <hi>Paul</hi> appeals to their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences: he tels them firſt, that in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things that were forbidden as well as Idolatry; as, Theft, Adultery, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> they could not but know themſelves guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty generally, as well as the Gentiles. He comes at laſt to that very thing, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in was their greateſt confidence, they were not Idolaters; <hi>Thou,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>that abhorreſt Idols, doſt thou commit ſacriledge?</hi>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:121169:41"/>I will not enquire how far the <hi>Jews</hi> were guilty of that great ſin, <hi>Sacriledge,</hi> in thoſe dayes: It is enough for our preſent occaſion, that St. <hi>Paul,</hi> to abate their confidence in that they moſt truſted to, doth object unto them one great ſin which they could not acquit them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves of: and it is poſſible, he did inſiſt upon <hi>Sacriledge</hi> particularly, as a prophet, for the inſtruction of after-ages, as foreſeeing that this horrible ſin of <hi>Sacriledge</hi> would be committed ordinari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and frequently (the time would come) under pretence of hatred to <hi>Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Well: we return where we began: as there is a day in the week, called <hi>The Lords Day:</hi> ſo there is a prayer as ordinarily called, in all ages ſince Chriſt, <hi>the Lords prayer:</hi> Both pretend unto the Lord, and the ſame <hi>Lord;</hi> the Saviour and Redeemer of the world. I would fain know what is the reaſon, that ſome ſhew ſo much zeal to the one, beyond what hath been known or pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:121169:42"/>in any age among Chriſtians, or is at this day, in any place of the world, beſides <hi>England,</hi> and thoſe places that have relation to it; grounding upon Scriptures, of which there is great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie, and variety of opinion among learned Proteſtants, as may appear by their Writings; and towards the other, of which never was any queſtion before, but unanimous both practiſe and opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, among Chriſtians of all ages; to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards that, they ſhew ſo little zeal and affection? Truly, I think, as our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, our obedience, ſhould be ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, and abſolute, if true and real: ſo ſhould our zeal too, if true zeal: Nay, St. <hi>James</hi> ſaith it poſitively, that true <hi>zeal,</hi> (he ſpeaks it of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; <hi>Wiſdome,</hi> immediately: but he began with <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: and what he ſayes of <hi>Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,</hi> belongs unto <hi>zeal,</hi> as the chief ſubject and occaſion: for ſo indeed the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ought to have been tranſlat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed here, as I conceive; <hi>Zeal:</hi> as well as <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.2. <hi>They have zeal,</hi> &amp;c. and
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:121169:42"/>not <hi>envying.</hi> No man doth <hi>glory</hi> of <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vying,</hi> but of <hi>zeal,</hi> many, God knows, without cauſe, 10.14. And <hi>verſe</hi> 16. <hi>Zeal</hi> and <hi>strife,</hi> or <hi>contention,</hi> that is, a contentious zeal, by a noted Scripture<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>figure) is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>without partiality:</hi> a pregnant weighty word.</p>
            <p>I will not enter into any diſputation here, or interpoſe any thing of mine own Judgement or Opinion, concerning the obſervation of the <hi>Lords day:</hi> This I ſay, which no man can deny: It can never be ſhewed, that ſuch pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſeneſs was ever uſed, or thought ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary in the obſervation of it, as is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired by ſome men. Firſt, for <hi>Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe:</hi> The firſt Emperour that was a Chriſtian, and ſetled Chriſtianity in the world, made a Law, it might be law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full (in caſe of unſeaſonable weather) to gather the fruits of the earth upon the Sunday. I know that Law was af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards repealed, and I know what is ſaid by ſome, it was made in favour of the Gentiles, and not for Chriſtians.
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:121169:43"/>I will not argue it here: but it is well known, there is enough to be ſaid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides of former times. If we look upon the practice of Proteſtant Churches, (which I think will go further with many) in <hi>Geneva,</hi> in <hi>Calvin</hi>'s time at leaſt, how then it was, cannot but be known unto moſt, becauſe obſerved by many: I will forbear the particulars. In the Low-Countries, till the Synod of <hi>Dort</hi> (it is a ſhame, I confeſs) no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing almoſt was unlawful upon that day: And it is obſerved in courſe of Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, Monks and Friers were the firſt, that brought this preciſeneſs in faſhion in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now for the Opinions of Proteſtant Divines beyond the ſeas, I know not of any at all, that have gone ſo far as the <hi>Engliſh:</hi> nayther indeed hath it been much queſtioned, till of late <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marus,</hi> a great <hi>Anti-Arminian</hi> (upon information perchance of what was done in <hi>England,</hi> under pretence of <hi>Zeal</hi>) his <hi>Inveſtigatio Sabbatbi,</hi> who in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:121169:43"/>doth go very far, as not allowing either name <hi>Diem Dominicum,</hi> in that ſenſe, as commonly underſtood, or <hi>thing</hi> as grounded upon any authority of either Old or New Teſtament. He was op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed by <hi>Dr. Riuet,</hi> the moſt authentick of theſe late times, but with great mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration; who alſo, though diſſenting in other things, doth yield unto him, (and <hi>Gomarus</hi> in his <hi>Reply,</hi> is not little pleaſed with it) that the obſervation of one day of ſeaven, hath no ground at all upon the fourth Commandment, or Old Teſtament. Dr. <hi>Prideaux,</hi> the publick Profeſſor of Divinity in <hi>Oxford</hi> for many years before theſe late wars, (a man generally accounted by the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſer ſort, as well as others, till this late Reformation, and that he was a Biſhop, both learned and godly) did publickly maintain at a ſolemn Act in <hi>Oxford,</hi> almoſt as much as <hi>Gomarus,</hi> and quotes divers Proteſtant Divines, as <hi>Calvin, Bullinger, Urſinus,</hi> and others, for his opinion. The Book is tranſlated
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:121169:44"/>into Engliſh: the Reader may do well not to reſt upon what I ſay, but to peruſe the book it ſelf, being made ſo common and vulgar: it may be, he will not repent his labour. <hi>Walaeus,</hi> another Proteſtant Divine, no obſcure man, neither; is the man, who, of all out-landiſh Writers I have ſeen, hath written, or may be thought to have written moſt, (though long before) in complyance to theſe times: yet even he, where he tells us of the <hi>Edicts</hi> of the Synod of <hi>Dort,</hi> for the more ſtrict ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of that day, commends their moderation, in that they did not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn them that were of a different opinion; in his <hi>Preface;</hi> and in his Book, he allows very well of <hi>Conſtantine</hi>'s Law, for liberty upon Sundayes in harveſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time, when the weather proves unſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable; as alſo of moderate and civil recreations upon that day, ſo it be after the publick ſervice of the day perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and not before, or between.</p>
            <p>Now for the Scriptures, which are
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:121169:44"/>the Rule of our faith, if a man look upon the Old Teſtament, upon a ſuppoſition, that what is there concerning the <hi>Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh</hi> Sabbath, is applyable (a thing not eaſily proved) to <hi>the Lords day,</hi> or Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day of the Chriſtians: ſo he ſhall find many things both in the Law, and in the Prophets, that may be thought to require great preciſeneſs. But if we look into the New Teſtament, (our moſt immediate Rule, as Chriſtians) there will not, neither in all that is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded of Chriſt, as either ſpoken or done by him in the four Goſpels; nor in all the Writings of his Apoſtles, any thing be found, that doth make that way, but rather to the contrary: which is ſome wonder, if it were ſo material to Chriſtianity: eſpecially, after ſo much recorded in the Goſpels of Chriſts ſpeeches, tending, in ordinary conſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, to the abrogation of that legal or ceremonial preciſeneſs. And it may be further obſerved, that thoſe (for the moſt part) who commonly preſs thoſe
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:121169:45"/>paſſages of the Old Teſtament, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the <hi>Sabbath,</hi> notwithſtanding that ſo much is to be ſaid againſt the pertinency of thoſe allegations: yet in other things, as in matter of <hi>uſury</hi> (con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the opinion and practiſe of moſt of the old Clergy, or <hi>prelatical men,</hi>) they can ſwallow abundance of Texts, which in all probability (though I conclude nothing) ſhould make it un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull, at leaſt, in Clergy men. For my part, as I ſaid before, I conclude nothing; and I hope the ingenuous cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable Reader, will not conclude from any thing I have ſaid of the <hi>Lords day,</hi> that I am againſt the religious, yea, and ſtrict (in ſome reſpects) obſerving of it. I am not, I never was: I will ſay more: if a man be not fully reſolved and ſatisfied about this point, but though he have taken pains to be ſatisfied, ſtands in a kind of <hi>Aequilibrium,</hi> or Even-bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance, between both opinions, ſo that for ought he knows either of them may prove true, or falſe; in ſuch a caſe, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:121169:45"/>that he condemn not others, that go another way; ſuch eſpecially, as do it with a <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> of faith and conſcience, as to themſelves, (men o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe religious in their life and converſation) and that he make it not a cloak of diſobedience, to oppoſe lawfull, Authority, which in all things lawfull or doubtfull, ought to be obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: in ſuch a caſe, Iſay, with theſe cautions we have inſerted: <hi>I</hi> hold it much ſafer, according to the old ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Peccare in meliorem partem:</hi> to be more preciſe, than he need perchance; then (for ought he knows) to take more liberty upon that day, than God hath allowed. But the caſe being ſo, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the <hi>Lords day,</hi> and the <hi>Lords Prayer:</hi> that of the one, no queſtion hath ever been among Chriſtians: of the other, (as to that which is required by ſome, that would be thought moſt zealous) much queſtion and controverſie: how this can ſtand with true <hi>impartial zeal</hi> and piety, that the one ſhould be ſo
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:121169:46"/>much preſſed; and the other ſo little regarded, I leave it to the unpartiall reader, his further and ſober conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>I might very well end here. For after ſo much light of Scripture, and ſo much weight of authority, (the beſt that can be deſired in a cauſe) I make ſome que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, whether it be ſo lawfull and war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantable, to give eare to any objection. What if a man will undertake to prove by Scripture, that there is no ſuch thing, as the Reſurection of the dead, or the immortality of the ſoul: there is Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture enough (it is true) for both; to ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy a man that is not wilfully blind, or factiouſly refractorie; a <hi>Quaker:</hi> an <hi>Anabaptiſt.</hi> However, he is but a poor Sophiſter, that cannot forme ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections, yea frame arguments (in ſhew) out of the Scriptures againſt both. To diſpute with ſuch, is to yield to them (ſo it may thought, at leaſt) that they have ſome ground to doubt: and that is ſome wrong to the truth. Not to hear them, I
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:121169:46"/>hold it generally the beſt courſe; both for them, (if not paſt all hopes) to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim them: and for others, to keep them within ſobrietie. However, after ſo much premiſed, becauſe all men are not of one temper, and ſome more taken with ſleight, then weight, in point of reaſon: I will take notice of ſuch objections that I have mett with, or could think any way con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable.</p>
            <p>Truely many are not ſo, eſpecially ſuch as I have met with in that <hi>Johnſon,</hi> before named. You ſhall have a taſte, if you pleaſe, that you may judge of the reſt. Heare then, I pray, one of his maine proofes, why what we call the <hi>Lords Prayer,</hi> cannot be a prayer: <hi>If it be ſo;</hi> ſaith he, <hi>as you ſay,</hi> (that, <hi>Our Father</hi> &amp;c. is a prayer) <hi>I would know of you, whoſe prayer ſhall it be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led? Chriſts: his Apostles: or ours? If you ſay Chriſts; why Christ did not ſo pray for himſelf: (elſe he that had no ſin, muſt be thought to have prayed for
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:121169:47"/>remiſsion of ſinnes, p.</hi> 22.) <hi>but taught his Diſciples ſo to pray. If you ſay, the Apostles: we do not finde in all the New Teſtament that they did ever uſe it. If you ſay: Ours: then it will follow, that we did pray before we were borne</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>I am ſo farre from thinking, that this wants any refutation, that I cannot otherwiſe think, when I reade it; but that the man had ſom diſtemper in his braines: and had I been acquainted with him, I would freindly have perſwaded him to have gone to a phyſician: I am very confident, good phyſick would do more good, (if themſelves could be perſwaded,) to many, great ſticklers, and much followed, (ſuch hath allwayes been the palate of the generalitie, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially when wordly ſucceſs doth coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance the act:) then all the arguing of the world. Well: you have had a taſt of this mans ſophiſtrie: you had my judgement of him before. In ſtead of a refutation, you ſhall hear what more
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:121169:47"/>ſober men (of theſe times) have written concerning this title, under which this <hi>holy prayer</hi> commonly paſſeth. Mr. <hi>Dan. Cawdry:</hi> and Mr. <hi>Herb. Palmer:</hi> members of the <hi>Aſſembly</hi> of Divines <hi>in Sabb. Rediv.</hi> or, <hi>the Chriſtian Sabbath.</hi> pag. 341. in the margin: over againſt theſe words in the Book: [Then beſides all that hath already been noted of the Lords Day, it is here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by alſo intitled to an Inſtitution from the the Lord himſelf: from Chriſt: as being paralell in phraſe, to the Lords ſupper: which beyond all peradventure, had no other inſtitution but Chriſt; &amp;c.] There, in the margin: [The primitive Church ſeems to bear witneſſe to this, calling the Prayer inſtituted by Chriſt, by the ſame terme, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: <hi>Oratio Dominica:</hi> neither can it ſignify any thing, but <hi>the prayer of the Lords institution,</hi> though the generations after, weakened this teſtimony, by calling <hi>Churches</hi> ſo.] I think, the laſt words, if they had thought fit, might have been ſpared: ſince it is certain that <hi>Churches</hi> were ſo called, for
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:121169:48"/>another reaſon; not becauſe inſtituted (particular Churches) <hi>by the Lord;</hi> but becauſe conſecrated (though now much abuſed, ſome by abominable profanation: &amp; others, in ſome places irreligiouſly pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led down, to build private houſes, or to make mony) <hi>to the Lord. Walaeus</hi> had told them ſo long a go: [<hi>Sed nec ea conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia est neceſſaria, quia</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>ſeu</hi> Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minicum <hi>vocari poteſt; non tantum quod ab ipſo Domino; ſed etiam quod ad ipſius memoriam, ut veteres loquuntur; aut in ipſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us honorem, et adipſius cultum eſt inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum: ſicut</hi> altare Domini, <hi>&amp;</hi> feſtum Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini, &amp;c.]</p>
            <p>The next objection, that I ſhall take notice of, is ſuch a one, as the Reader perchance would not have expected, but I cannot ſatisfy my conſcience, if I ſhould conceale that from him, which, I confeſs, hath troubled me more, then all that I have read of that nature. I tooke notice before of what ſome particular men had ſaid of this <hi>holy prayer,</hi> as <hi>Luther, Calvin,</hi> and others. Now I ſhall tell the Reader
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:121169:48"/>with greif, I find learned Mr. <hi>Hugo Grotius,</hi> moſt cold in this point. For though he alſo ſay, <hi>(quod cum fructu fieri poteſt:)</hi> that is, he allowes the <hi>Lords prayer</hi> to be uſed as a Prayer, and ſaith it may be done profitably: yet taking all his words together upon this occaſion, I know not how to excuſe him. We ſhall conſider of ſome of them by and by. In the mean time, I would not have any man, either to wonder at it, or to value much his authority herein. There is no man can ſpeake ſo highly of him, either of his parts, or performances in all kind of learning, but I ſhall willingly ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe. However, nothing can be ſaid of him ſo high, that can make me think him more then a man, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: <hi>a mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Creature, by nature</hi> (as Plato well de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined him) as well in the affections of his ſoule, opinions of his minde; as temper, and condition of body. <hi>Salomon</hi> was a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table example; and after him, we need not wonder at any man. What hapned to <hi>Grotius</hi> in his latter dayes; I am loath
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:121169:49"/>to ſay: I wiſh his own books; <hi>Annotati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> upon the Scripture, and others ſince, did not ſo evidently proclaime. They that labour to excuſe him, if any do, they but <hi>laterem lavare:</hi> and will ſooner bring themſelves into ſuſpicion, than acquit him. Among other his extravagant con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits of his old age, one was, <hi>De communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cando ſine Symbolis:</hi> or, <hi>Sine pastore;</hi> or to that effect: for I have it not at this time: which was anſwered by <hi>Sirmondus,</hi> or <hi>Petavius</hi> (I know not which: I am grown ſuch a ſtranger ſince theſe times of <hi>Reformation</hi> to thoſe books I once had and read) and as I take it, he made ſome kind of recantation, by diſavowing part of it. No wonder therefore, I ſay, if <hi>Grotius</hi> was no better friend (at that time) as to ſet prayers, in generall; ſo particularly, to this incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable pattern and preſident of all ſet prayers, and preſcript formes. But <hi>Gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius,</hi> when trueſt <hi>Grotius,</hi> was I know, and can ſay it; a great admirer of the Church of England, as ſetled under King
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:121169:49"/>
               <hi>Charls</hi> the firſt, and other Princes of happy memory. Let the Reader gueſſe, to uſe no other arguments at this time; by what he wrote to me in a letter A. D. 1639. of Hooker his <hi>Eccleſiaſtical policie</hi> [Richardi Hookeri <hi>ſcripta ante annos multos vidi, &amp; quanquam in ſermone mihi non percognito, facile cognovi exactiſſimi Operis utilitatem: quae tanta eſt, ut hunt quoque librum Verti, ſed in Latinum ſermonem pervelim. quaero ſi quis hic est, qui id efficere cupiat. caeterùm tibi id ipſum cordi eſſe velim.]</hi> Hence doth appeare, how deſirous he was, that <hi>Hookers</hi> bookes were turned into Latin, for the good he expected they would do, if more generally known. We have them in Engliſh, God be prayſed: but do we reade them? In very deed, ſuch is my opinion of that incomparable worke, that did not I believe the world (that is, the greateſt number of men) really mad, in the true Stoicall ſence: and that it is ſome degree of madneſs (eſpecially, after long warrs; confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions and alterations of ſtates) to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:121169:50"/>it otherwiſe: I would perſwade men that have been buyers of books theſe 15. or 16. yeares laſt paſt, to burn one halfe, at leaſt, of thoſe bookes they have bought, (they were as good do ſo, as to fell them for nothing) and to betake themſelves to the reading of <hi>Hooker:</hi> not doubting, but by that time they had read him once, or twice over accuratly, they would thank me for my ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice; but God, much more, that put it into their hearts to follow it.</p>
            <p>It may be ſome Readers would be better ſatisfyed, if I had produced the whole letter from which that paſſage was taken: others, more likely, ſhould I do it, would think I ſought occaſion to let the world know, how great I was, with that <hi>Great man.</hi> Truly, if the firſt will be granted unto me, I will not ſtick at the latter. I never was very prone to to ſeek acquaintances: I have had ſome opportunities, which I have declined. But Mr. <hi>Grotius</hi> did me the honour (Mr.
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:121169:50"/>
               <hi>Voſsius</hi> I think perſwaded him) to write to me the firſt letter, and ſo begun our acquaintance and communication. And truly, I will confeſs, I did aſcribe ſo much unto his worth, and ſingular in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity, I was not leſs proud (though I think not many can ſay, they ever heard me brag of it; nor any, that I ſhewed his Letters) of his acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, then if it had been with the greateſt Prince of <hi>Europe.</hi> And though my love to the truth, hath compelled me to acknowledge ſo much of his incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy in his latter dayes; yet my com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort is, (I have reaſon to believe it, as I have elſewhere declared) he dyed a good Chriſtian, and a Proteſtant; and my hope is, he hath a reward in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, for his zeal to the Chriſtian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, for which he hath written ſo excellently well, and his continual de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire and endeavours for peace: beſides his other performances, by which the honour of Learning hath been ſo much advanced. And if I may ſpeak the
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:121169:51"/>truth without offence, I verily believe his great diſlike of our doings in <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland,</hi> was no ſmall occaſion of his fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling out with our Religion: beſides the unkind dealing, and vigorous oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſome of his own Countrey, from whom he might have expected more fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, having raiſed that Nation to the higheſt pitch of Glory (in point of learning) that any Nation hath attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unto. Well, I am willing to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, that ſome Reader will deſire to ſee the letter: but however that it may give leſs offence, (if any offence at all) it ſhall not be here, but at the end, where it may be taken in, or left, as the Reader ſhall think fit.</p>
            <p>This great block in my way removed, as I hope it is, we proceed to objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. We do not find, ſay ſome, (and I find it in <hi>Grotius</hi> too) upon any Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord of Scripture, that either Chriſt, or his Apoſtles, did uſe this prayer. We ſaid before, he doth not deny, but it may be done <hi>cum fructu:</hi> but he doth
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:121169:51"/>not make that the chief, or principal uſe of it. For my part, grant me the uſe of it as a Prayer, and ſo intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Chriſt himſelf: I think it very needleſs to contend with any man about the reſt: whether intended principally as a <hi>Prayer,</hi> or a direction to <hi>Prayer.</hi> If it be a Prayer, there is no queſtion to be made, and it will follow by ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary conſequence, that it is a <hi>Dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi> of Prayer alſo, as it is his prayer, who ſpake nothing, did nothing, but is ſet out unto us for our (according to our power) imitation; our Lord and Maſter <hi>Jeſus Christ.</hi> Yet if we muſt ſay ſomewhat to that buſineſs, I would ſay, but without contention, I ſhould think that principally intended by Chriſt, which was moſt direct and pertinent to the requeſt, made unto him by his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciples. Now if it be granted, (which hath been ſpoken to before) that what his Diſciples deſired, was a form of Prayer: what will follow upon it, any man may gather. But I determine no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:121169:52"/>peremtorily: I will leave every man to his own Judgement, in this par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular. Well, the objection is, We do not find that Chriſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as before. I know that <hi>Grotius</hi> is not the firſt that hath ſo argued: I am ſorry it can be ſaid, that a man of his judgement did ever entertain this, as a material ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection. No ſober man, I think (and this alſo before ſpoken of,) will deny, but that a very form of bleſſing is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed by God, <hi>Numb.</hi> 6.23. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Yet we do not find it in the whole Scripture. Again, We have a form of baptizing preſcribed. <hi>Mat.</hi> 28. by Chriſt himſelf, <hi>In the name of the Father, &amp;c.</hi> but no ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of it elſewhere, that I know of in the New Teſtament, though we read of many baptized by the Apoſtles and others: and I think to this day, is a form of Baptiſm among Chriſtians, in all places. We might inſiſt in many more ſuch things; out of the Old and New Teſtament, if need were.</p>
            <p>Some preſs this further: not only this Prayer is not found uſed, as a
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:121169:52"/>Prayer, but neither in the <hi>Acts,</hi> nor any of the <hi>Epiſtles,</hi> though divers things concerning Prayer in general, are there preſcribed: yet no mention at all of this Prayer is made. This may be thought to have a ſhew of ſomewhat: but in effect, it proves nothing, as by divers inſtances, of the ſame nature, if fearch be made, will appear. <hi>Act.</hi> 20.35. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; is mentioned, as one of Chriſt his me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morable ſayings, which yet in none of the fouer Evangeliſts is found. We can make but a negative argument of it, which at the beſt is of no great vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity: but after ſuch evidence of poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive proofes, is very impertinent.</p>
            <p>But yet I cannot tell, whether it may ſo peremptorily be affirmed, that no mention at all, expreſs or implicite, is made of the <hi>Lords prayer</hi> in the Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of his Apoſtles. There may ſome places be found perchance, where it may not improbably be thought alluded unto by ſome words. When the Apoſtles tells
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:121169:53"/>us in ſeveral places, that this or that <hi>is the Will of God:</hi> they do it often, and emphatically, ſometimes; who can tell, but it was with ſome tacit re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference and alluſion, to the words of the <hi>Lords prayer,</hi> which they knew were dayly repeated and aſſented unto, by thoſe primitive Chriſtians they wrote unto, and therefore might enforce their exhortation to ſuch and ſuch duties, from their own ſecret conſent, includ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and expreſſed in their daily prayer? But ſince this occaſion is given me, I ſhall crave leave I may but propoſe what, long before I had any the leaſt ſuſpition, that ever the <hi>Lords Prayer</hi> ſhould want any defence in <hi>England,</hi> had been in my thoughts. I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, I ſee men take ſo much liberty, I have no great fancy to new interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations. I had much rather (were I to write upon the Scripture) defend one old received interpretation upon good grounds of reaſon, than be the author of two new, though probable. This
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:121169:53"/>makes me to ſuſpect the more, what I have to ſay, becauſe I find it no where. But becauſe it was in my thoughts, as I ſaid before, long before I had any thought of this occaſion; in that reſpect, I ſuſpect it leſs. In thoſe words of St. <hi>Peter, chap.</hi> 1. <hi>verſ.</hi> 17. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I have thought it very probable, that he might intend the <hi>Lords prayer.</hi> Firſt, That the word, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, doth properly (and ſo commonly uſed in the New Teſtament) ſignifie, <hi>To call upon in prayer;</hi> and generally, <hi>To pray,</hi> will eaſily be granted I know. <hi>Beza</hi> tranſlates, <hi>Si cognominatis patrem:</hi> The words may be tranſlated, <hi>If you call upon him as Father,</hi> or, <hi>If in praying, you call him Father.</hi> Well, here is no great alteration in this, from what is commonly received. But what can we infer upon this, that will more particularly concern the <hi>Lords prayer?</hi> I ground chieſly upon the words following, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:121169:54"/>which indeed ſeeme to promiſe leaſt: yea, to croſs rather what we would have: but, if well examined, it may prove otherwiſe. I muſt here appeal to the <hi>Hebrew Idiotiſm,</hi> whereof the New Teſtament (though written in <hi>Greek</hi>) is full. As for example, <hi>Acts</hi> 8.20. (a common example) where the Original hath it, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: it is rendred very truly in the Engliſh, <hi>exceeding fair,</hi> without any mention of God, which is in the Original words, and might ſeem ſtrange to them that are not acquainted with the <hi>Hebrew</hi> phraſe: to them that are, not at all: and ſo of divers places. Upon this ground of the <hi>Hebrew Idiotiſm,</hi> I think it may be ſaid, <hi>That to be in heaven,</hi> as in <hi>the Lords prayer; (Our Father which art in Heaven:)</hi> and, <hi>To judge without reſpect of perſous,</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) <hi>accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to every mans work:</hi> as in St. <hi>Peter,</hi> may amount to one and the ſame ſenſe. For proof whereof, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 115.2, 3. <hi>Wherefore ſhould the heathen ſay, where is
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:121169:54"/>now their God? But our God is in the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens; he hath done whatſoever he pleaſeth.</hi> The Pſalmiſt, out of doubt, and ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded by ſome Antients, intended by theſe words, that although God, for ſome ſecret cauſes, beſt known to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, did defer the execution of his ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, or juſt vengeance upon them, who had uſed his people ſo and ſo: yet in <hi>heaven</hi> he was for all that: want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed neither power, nor will, but in due time would reward them, both them that had done, and them that had ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered wrong, according to their deſerts. We ſay ſtill, when we appeal to God, upon occaſion of wrong and oppreſſion, <hi>There is a God in Heaven.</hi> But if this be not expreſs enough, I hope the next will be. Pſalm 7.6, 7. <hi>Ariſe, O Lord, in thine Anger; lift up thy ſelf, becauſe of the rage of mine enemies; and awake for me to the judgement, that thou haſt commanded. So ſhall the congregation of the people compaſs thee about: for their ſakes therefore return thou on High. Return
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:121169:55"/>thou on high,</hi> that is, <hi>to heaven:</hi> (ſo the ſenſe doth require; and all the <hi>Rabbins</hi> agree:) from whence God, as to the appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion of men, is ſuppoſed to abſent himſelf, when he doth not execute judgement, but ſuffers the wicked to prevail in this world, as we ſee he doth often. The Reaſon of this ſpeech, is, Heaven is, properly, the Throne of God. <hi>Heaven is my Throne, the earth is my foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtool,</hi> (Pſalm 66.1.) Now <hi>Thrones</hi> among men, are chiefly eſtabliſhed for, and by Juſtice; therefore when Gods Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice doth not appear among men, they ſuppoſe him, for a time, not to be in his <hi>Throne,</hi> that is, in Heaven. There be many phraſes in Scripture, in the Pſalms eſpecially, that have reference to this, which we have ſpoken of elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where (<hi>Annot.</hi> upon <hi>Pſalm</hi> 7. <hi>v.</hi> 7.56.2.68.18. <hi>&amp; alibi.</hi>) Interpreters that ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve not this <hi>Idiotiſm,</hi> are put to it. I only obſerve more, that preſently after theſe words in the <hi>Pſalm, Return thou on high:</hi> it follows, <hi>The Lord ſhall judge
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:121169:55"/>the people: judge me, O Lord,</hi> as if he had ſaid, No ſooner is God returned to his place, his <hi>Throne,</hi> his <hi>Heavens,</hi> but we ſhall be ſure to hear of Juſtice, and juſt judgements executed. The truth is, God is alwayes in Heaven: alwayes juſt: nay, alwayes doing ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice. For what is more juſt and reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, than to ſuffer them to be exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed in this world, for a while, with temporary afflictions and oppreſſions; whom he hath deſtinated to eternal hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs in the Kingdome of heaven? And to ſuffer them to prevail and proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, for a while, (though not alwayes ſo neither: And God knows, how in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderable a time, compared to E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity) who for their wickedneſs and infidelity, are to undergo ſuch an eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of darkneſs and miſery? <hi>Which is a manifeſt Token,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>of the righteous judgement of God, that ye may be counted worthy of the Kingdome of God, for which ye alſo ſuffer, ſeeing it is a righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous thing with God,</hi> &amp;c. And in the
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:121169:56"/>parable of the <hi>Rich man</hi> and <hi>Lazarus, Son, remember that thou in thy life time, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivedst thy good things, and likewiſe</hi> La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarus <hi>evil things: but now he is comforted, and thou art tormented.</hi> But theſe things, though certain and true to the eye of Faith, (confirmed alſo by ſound and ſolid Reaſon, if well looked into) yet, not ſo apprehended, ordinarily. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Pſalmiſt ſaith in a place, <hi>That God is known</hi> (in the world) <hi>by the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which he executeth.</hi> So then, God (in one ſenſe, for we exclude not others, as we ſhall ſay by and by;) is ſaid, <hi>To be in heaven, to return on high;</hi> or, <hi>to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven:</hi> when he doth adminiſter Juſtice, or juſt Judgements: or (to ſpeak yet more particularly) <hi>When by thoſe judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments he executeth; viz</hi> rewarding the good and bad, faithfull and Infidels, <hi>accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to their deeds:</hi> he doth manifeſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf a juſt God. According to this ſenſe, thoſe words in the Lords prayer, <hi>Our Father which art in Heaven,</hi> are not only alluded unto, but fully paraphraſed by
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:121169:56"/>St. <hi>Peter,</hi> when he ſaith, <hi>And if ye call on the Father</hi> (or, as we ſaid the words may be rendred, <hi>If ye call him Father, when ye pray) who without reſpect of perſons, judgeth according to every mans work, paſs the time,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Beſides this, the coherence is much better by this interpretation. The Apoſtle, immediately before, uſed an argument to preſſe to holineſſe, becauſe <hi>God is holy:</hi> and to make his argument more weighty, he quotes Scripture for it: <hi>For it is written, be ye holy,</hi> &amp;c. He proceeds here, and grounds another duty, to wit, holy fear, upon our relation to God, as a <hi>Father.</hi> Now though it be true that impartiall juſtice, may belong to a <hi>Father:</hi> yet the ground of this depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and <hi>St. Peter</hi>'s inference, is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what obſcure, except he allude and ground upon the words in <hi>the Lords prayer,</hi> and their connexion there, <hi>Our Father, which art in heaven:</hi> according to that interpretation, we have ſpoken of, which to them that St. <hi>Peter</hi> wrote unto, could
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:121169:57"/>not but be familiar enough. And this is as much, as if he had, here alſo, quoted Scripture. As if he had ſaid: Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber and conſider well, that in your day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly prayer, preſcribed unto you by Chriſt himſelf: as you call God, your Father, <hi>Our Father;</hi> which may ſeem to promiſe indulgence: ſo you adde, <hi>which art in heaven:</hi> to put you in mind, that God is juſt; impartiall, <hi>who without reſpect of perſons, judgeth according to every mans work,</hi> which as I ſaid, is equivalent to that quotation of Scripture in the former <hi>ver.</hi> Which nevertheles if it be granted, or ſupoſed to have been St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, it doth not follow, that thoſe words in the Lords prayer, <hi>which art in heaven:</hi> admit of no other ſence; or that St. <hi>Peter</hi> would have it ſo. It is enough, if the words will bear this ſenſe alſo, without any violence offered unto them. But this, as I ſaid at firſt, I propoſe as not impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable, and no otherwiſe; not ſo much in anſwer to what is objected (which needes it not:) as to contribute ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what,
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:121169:57"/>(occaſion being given) towards the right, or at leaſt, probable under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of a place of Scripture.</p>
            <p>Another Objection is: If thoſe words <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>ſay ye;</hi> muſt be underſtood lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erally, then we muſt never pray other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, but uſe thoſe very words allways: and ſo, no other prayer, but <hi>the Lords prayer,</hi> ſhall be lawfull. But this we know is againſt the practiſe of all Churches, from the beginning: whence they would inferre, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Here I ſhall ſay, what common ſenſe might ſuggeſt, unto any man; It is one thing to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>and words <hi>literally;</hi> another thing, <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſely peeviſhly:</hi> or to ſpeake more plainly, <hi>maliciouſly.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: <hi>pray allwayes,</hi> or <hi>without ceaſing,</hi> 1 Theſ. v. 16. But this we know, <hi>preciſely</hi> taken, cannot be: nay, contrary to other places and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions of Scripture. Therefore the Apoſtle doth not meane it, of real and literal praying. The Apoſtle ſaith: <hi>Children, obey your parents in all things. Col.</hi> 3.20. but this we know, <hi>preciſely</hi> taken,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:121169:58"/>ought not to be. For Parents may com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand many things, and do often, contrary to the law of God. Therefore the Apoſtle intended it not of literall real obedience: or, not of carnal parents. A hundred ſuch places we might produce: but theſe may ſuffice to ſhew the abſurdity and iniquity of this kind of argumenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. But, I ſay ſtill: When, and where, there is good evidence for the literal meaning. In doubtfull places, a man may uſe his diſcretion.</p>
            <p>I ſay Secondly: By the very circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of the Text, it may be gathered, that Chriſts anſwer did not tend unto this, to forbid men other prayers. <hi>Teach us to pray, as</hi> Iohn <hi>did his Diſciples,</hi> not, <hi>teach us to pray;</hi> barely, and abſolutely. Or, what we ſhall ſay when we pray: but, <hi>as</hi> John <hi>taught his Diſciples;</hi> ſo teach us alſo ſome particular forme, whereby we may be known unto others thy Diſciples: and which our ſelves may uſe with confidence at all times as an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtionable, unparallel'd forme. <hi>Teach us: us:</hi> in common: ſuch a prayer
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:121169:58"/>therefore, that may ſit all men, at all times. But we know, that as the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of men upon earth, (ſome rich: ſome poore: ſome married, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) is very different: ſo muſt their occaſions of pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: nay, the ſame men have not allways the ſame occaſions. Very unlikely there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, that ſuch a prayer ſhould either be expected by the Diſciples, or intended by Chriſt that ſhould be of ſuch an extent, as ſhould include all particular occaſions. But however, if the emphaſis of the word uſed by Chriſt, to endeare this pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er unto us, and to prevent all evaſions, had any ambiguity in it: yet God be thanked, there be Scriptures enough, (beſides the conſtant uſe of the Church,) to take it away, and to ſatisfy the moſt ſcrupulous. Neither, indeed, do I hear of any, (what future times may produce, I know not) that makes any ſcruple, to pray in a Church with the Aſſembly; (<hi>Quakers,</hi> and <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptists,</hi> I meddle not with:) or in his houſe, with his family; becauſe
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:121169:59"/>Chriſt hath ſaid, <hi>When thou prayeſt, enter into thy Cloſet: and when thou haſt ſhut thy door,</hi> &amp;c. So that this is a meer cavil. I wiſh ſome would take more notice of thoſe words there: <hi>Uſe not vain Repetitions, as the heathen do: for they think they ſhall be heard for their much ſpeaking.</hi> The words, I think, are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs enough; and I know no inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nience, that would come of it, but that ſome men would looſe ſomewhat of that contentment they find in the length of their prayers, upon a pleaſing conceit of immediate inſpiration.</p>
            <p>But yet after all this, let me add, though the <hi>Lords prayer,</hi> doth not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude other prayers, private, or publick, not upon particular occaſions only, but at no time: and that we have warrant enough from Scripture for ſuch: and that to be able to expreſs himſelf, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all occaſions, both publickly, and privately (many can privately, who have not the confidence to do it publick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) readily and fluently: but, perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently,
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:121169:59"/>and reverently withal; is to be accounted a great gift: which though all men have not, (not the beſt; the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedſt ſometimes:) yet all men ſhould deſire, and honour it in others, that are Orthodox and Religious, (for it is well known, that ſome that were neyther, have had it in a large meaſure:) yet after all this, I ſay, I muſt add, that the <hi>Lords Prayer,</hi> with little, or no al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration at all, may be uſed upon parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular occaſions, whether publick or pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate; yea, and repeated (for which we have Chriſts warrant and example: <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.44. <hi>And he left them, and went away again, and prayed the third time ſaying the ſame words; O my Father, if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> be poſsible, let this cup paſs from me; ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs, not as I will, but as thou wilt, verſe</hi> 39. and 42.) to very good purpoſe, as I conceive. For when we have once opened our caſe before God, and what our hearts incline us to deſire, being of it ſelf lawfull and warrantable: this done, if preſently we betake our ſelves
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:121169:60"/>to the <hi>Lords Prayer: Thy Will be done in earth:</hi> or as Chriſt himſelf, to the ſame effect; <hi>Nevertheleſs, not my will, but thy Will be done:</hi> I think our prayers might prove more acceptable to God, more profitable to us, then often, when we long inſiſt upon our deſires. For God knows, ſuch is our ignorance, we ſeldome know, what is beſt, or expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient: and it often falls out, that when we have obtained what we prayed for, we have afterwards occaſion to curſe the hour, that it ever came into our hearts to pray for ſuch things. This is a point that hath been handled by Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ets and Philoſophers, (as was before intimated:) but very little underſtood and practiſed by many Chriſtians: not by them, I am ſure, who not only pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe and preſs, very peremptorily, what God ſhall grant: but alſo are rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to quarrel and expoſtulate with him, if they have not what they ask. And this is called <hi>zeal;</hi> when it is done by way of prayer: which would be little
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:121169:60"/>better than <hi>Blaſphemy,</hi> in ordinary rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoning.</p>
            <p>We ſee dayly, how many things fall out contrary to expectation. I would ask our brethren, the <hi>Scots,</hi> (without offence, I hope) when they prayed ſo zealouſly in their Churches, for the ſucceſs of their own, and the Engliſh Armies againſt their Soveraign, they then thought or believed, they prayed for their own confuſion: and that the time would come, within few years after, and the ſame Parliament yet ſitting, that we ſhould give God thanks in our Churches, for killing them in the field? Or that Politick noble man, who when truſted by the King to reconcile differences in <hi>Scotland,</hi> did foment them under hand; would he have thought, when he ſaw his policy to ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed, and hugg'd himſelf in his boſome for it; that the end of it within a while, would be, the looſing of his head upon a Scaffold, by thoſe men, whom his plots had raiſed, and his hands ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned?
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:121169:61"/>There is ſtore of ſuch publick ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples, which every man may ſuggeſt unto himſelf. [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: <hi>Thus did he pray; but, O the blindneſs of his mind! In that he pray'd, and had; his death and woe did find.</hi> Hom] But to inſiſt in more &amp; ſamiliar private experience. One main ſubject of private devotions, are Children: <hi>Ut ſint ſuperstites,</hi> that they may live; and according to the courſe of nature, out-live us. The very word <hi>Superſtitio,</hi> once a good word, (taken for <hi>Religion,</hi> in general) had its Original from thence, as <hi>Cicero</hi> ſomewhere doth teach. Whatſoever is objected by <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctantius,</hi> or any other againſt it, is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry impertinent; as to them that are verſed in theſe things, will appear. Moſt antient Heathens, when they treat of <hi>Superſtition,</hi> inſiſt upon this particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar of Parents. Now if we ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal to davly experience: How many Fathers and Mothers, who prayed for ſuch and ſuch Children, before they had them; or, when ſick, or in danger, as
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:121169:61"/>the only thing almoſt that made them happy, and which they would expect from God, in this world at leaſt; after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards have thought both themſelves, and thoſe very Children, had been ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry happy, if they had never been born, or dyed young: and that God had been very mercifull unto them, if he had not heard their prayers? It is ſo, of all worldly things. <hi>habet has vices conditio mortalium, ut adverſa exſecundis; ex ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſis, ſecunda naſcantur. Occultat utro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſemina Deus, &amp; plerumque bonorum malorum<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> cauſae ſub diverſa ſpecie latent.</hi> So the Orator, very wiſely and truly. How then can it be otherwiſe? The Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mick therefore, not leſs truly, than ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gantly.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Stulti haud ſcimus, quam fruſtra ſimus, quum quod cupienter dari Petimus nobis; quaſi quid in rem ſit, poſſimus noſcere. Certa amittimus, dum incerta petimus, atque hoc evenit In labore atque in dolore, ut mors obrepat interim.</hi>
            </q>
            <pb n="106" facs="tcp:121169:62"/>
            <p> How much ſafer then (as we ſaid before) when we have laid open our caſe and preſent apprehenſions upon it, before God: to betake our ſelves to this <hi>Holy Prayer,</hi> which from his authority, that commended it to us, and other good conſiderations that ſhould endear it to us, will both teach and help us, to ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate our hearts from thoſe wordly tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitory petty things, Wives, Hu bands, Children, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in compariſon) into better objects: The glory of our Creatour in heaven: the advancement of his Truth, in the world: humble ſubmiſſion to his heavenly Will and Wiſdome, in all things, from whom all that is truly good, and nothing but good doth proceed: from which things ſo thought upon and deſired, as we are taught by this <hi>Holy Prayer,</hi> our own eternal happineſs doth depend. And here it may be obſerved, that whereas; <hi>Mat</hi> 7.2. it is ſaid, <hi>If ye then being evil, know how to give good gifts unto your Children: how much more ſhall your Father, which is in beaven, give
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:121169:62"/>things to them that ask him?</hi> In St. <hi>Luke</hi> we find it, <hi>If ye then being evil, know how to give good things unto your Children, how much more ſhall your heavenly Father, give the holy Spirit to them that ask him:</hi> as if, (heavenly things, encreaſe of Grace,) that, the only thing either con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable, or that we can ſafely &amp; ſecure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pray for. And if we ſo uſe the <hi>Lords Prayer,</hi> with theſe thoughts; this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration of heart; we may (I ſaid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore) if occaſion be, uſe it often in one day, to our great comfort, and with leſs ſuperſtition I dare ſay, than ſome others their <hi>Battologies,</hi> or affected long prayers, condemned both in the Old and New Teſtament. All this while I have not forgotten what St. <hi>James</hi> ſaith, <hi>The ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectual fervent prayer of a righteous man, availeth much.</hi> Elias <hi>was a man,</hi> &amp;c. Though ſomewhat might be ſaid to that particular caſe: there be extraordinary times and occaſions; yea, and perſons too: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: <hi>of the ſame nature, as we are; Mortals, ſimiles aliis</hi> (as the vulgar
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:121169:63"/>Latin very well, <hi>Acts</hi> 14.15. not Gods) yet endowed with extraordiuary zeal, and raiſed of purpoſe ſometimes, for ſome extraordinary Act: but we have ſaid enough already, to prevent Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumny, as though we diſliked others, whilſt we commend and vindicate the <hi>Lords prayer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To tell us, that this prayer hath been, or is yet, (being mumbled upon beads, in an unknown language, and the like) much abuſed, and to make that an ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection againſt the uſe of it, after it hath been ſo cleerly proved, that no one duty of Chriſtian Religion, can pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to more evidence, of either Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture-authority, or univerſal conſent: every man that is not very ſimple and ignorant, muſt needs underſtand, what will be the conſequent of ſuch an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument. For what was ever, or is yet more abuſed, than the divine Scriptures; what more than praying or preaching? what more than Religion in genetal? under the mask whereof, what miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefs?
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:121169:63"/>what miſcarriages, both pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick and private have been contrived? What indeed is ſo generally abhorred among men, that hath not been acted under that ſacred name? Neyther is it ſo among Chriſtianr only. Look into ancient ſtories, when Paganiſm was the Religion of the world: look into latter ſtories of the Turks, or any other Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: even now the preſent diviſions of the Turks among themſelves (as our <hi>News books</hi> tell us) go under the name of <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Reformation: Tantum relligio potuit ſuadere malorum:</hi> in every mans mouth, and obſervation. And of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion particularly, we are told in ſome late <hi>Relations,</hi> that the <hi>Turks</hi> themſelves, (ſome of them, at leaſt) confefs Chriſtian Religion, to have been a good Religion for a long time, till it came to be corrupted, and abuſed by the Profeſſours of it: which, they ſay, made God to ſend <hi>Mahomes,</hi> to eſtabliſh a new. This may ſerve for a warning to others: ſober men will not uſe ſuch argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
            <pb n="180" facs="tcp:121169:64"/>
            <p> We did promiſe, Mr. <hi>Perkins</hi> before. his words are theſe, <hi>And whereas ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry men in our Church</hi> (I muſt appeal to the knowledge of them that know more than I; for in all my time, I never heard of any: except, Mr. <hi>Perkins</hi> underſtood, men that were borne of the Church of England; but ſince divided from it, by faction and ſingularity: ſuch as the forenamed <hi>Johnſon;</hi> and his adherents) <hi>hold it unlawfull to uſe this very form of words, as they are ſet down by our Saviour Chriſt, for a prayer; they are far deceived, as will appear by their reaſons. First, ſay they, it is Scripture; and therefore not to be uſed as a Prayer. I anſwer: that the ſame thing may be the Scripture of God, and alſo the prayer of man: elſe, the prayers of</hi> Moſes, David, <hi>and</hi> Paul, <hi>being ſet down in the Scripture; ceaſe to be prayers. again ſay they: That in prayer we are to expreſſe our Wants in particular, and the Graces which we deſire. Now in thoſe words, all things to be prayed for, are onely in general propounded: I anſwer. That the maine wants
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:121169:64"/>that are in any man, and the principal Graces of God to be deſired, are ſet down in the petitions of this prayer in particuler. Thirdly, they plead, that the patterne to make all prayer by, ſhould not be uſed as a Prayer. I anſwer, that therefore the rather it may beuſed as a Prayer: &amp; ſure it is, that ancient, and worthy Divines, have reverenced it as a prayer, chuſing rather to uſe theſe words, then any other:</hi> as <hi>Cyprian</hi> De Orat. Domini, and <hi>Tertul. lib.</hi> de ſugâ in perſecut. and <hi>Auguſt.</hi> ſerm. 12.6, de tempore. <hi>Wherefore this opinion is full of ignorance and error.</hi> So he. You may ſee by the begining, that Mr. <hi>Perkins</hi> had no mind (by acknowledging them of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> in thoſe dayes) to deale with them, as another man might have thought they had deſerved. Yet it is ſomewhat, that even he did charg them of groſſe ignorance, and error.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> have done with objections. There may be more, but I do not think them conſiderable: and there will be no end, if we muſt heare, or the Reader be told,
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:121169:65"/>what any man can ſay. I will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude all with thoſe excellent words (though indeed the ſubſtance of them is in <hi>St. Cyprian</hi>) I find in the book intitled, <hi>A Collection of Private Devotions &amp;c.</hi> of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten printed: (and well deſerving it:) in the preface of it: <hi>A prayer</hi> [the Lords prayer] <hi>whereby we have not only Chriſts own name, to countenance our ſuits</hi> (in whoſe name if we aske any thing, we ſhall have it: <hi>ſaith the Goſpell:) but Chriſts own words alſo, who himſelf is our Aduocate: and being beſt acquainted with the Lawes, and phraſes of his Fathers Court, hath drawn up ſuch a Bill for us, both for matter and form, as ſhall make our ſupplications acceptable and prevalent with Almighty God. And though men ſhould ſpeak with Angels tongues, yet words ſo pleaſing to the ears of God, as thoſe which the Son of God did compoſe, cannot poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly be uttered, nor any prayers ſo well fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, as thoſe that are made by this pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div xml:lang="lat" type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:121169:65"/>
            <head>The Letter mentioned, and promiſed here, <hi>Pag. 84.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">Reverendo viro, <hi>D.</hi> Merico Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaubono, Presbytero, Canonico Eccleſiae Primitialis Cantuari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enſis.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Vir Reverende,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Animarum te curam gerere, nec <hi>Cantuarienſium</hi> tantum &amp; <hi>Anglicarum,</hi> ſed &amp; externarum,
<pb facs="tcp:121169:66"/>
               <hi>ſatis oſtendunt, tot miſſa ad me mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nera, talia omnia, ex quibus &amp; ego poſſim fieri melior, &amp; alii qui per me beneficii tui participes fient.</hi> Theophylactus, <hi>Graecorum ante ſe compendium, velut vox eſt Graecae Eccleſiae,</hi> Pauli <hi>ſenſa bona fide cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtodita, nobis exhibens. Acta Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gem veſtrum optimum,</hi> Scotosque <hi>inter, non quidem efficient, ut ego motus illos feroces, imo feros, quos damnavi ſemper, magis damnem; ſed ut quod mihi ſemper viſum fuit, aliis etiam firmè perſuadeam. Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum autem refert exiſtimationis Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giae, haec acta verti in</hi> Gallicum <hi>ſermonem, nec quieſcam donec ei la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bori aliquem idoneum invenero, &amp; ad
<pb facs="tcp:121169:66"/>id animavero.</hi> Richardi Hookeri <hi>ſcripta, ante annos multos vidi; &amp; quanquam in ſermone mihi non per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cognito, facile cognovi exactiſſimi operis utilitatem: quae tanta eſt, ut hunc quoque librunt verti, ſed in la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinum ſermonem pervelim. Quaeram ſi quis hic eſt, qui idefficere cupiat. Caeterum &amp; tibiid ipſum cordi eſse velim.</hi> Anglicana <hi>verſio libri no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtri pro veritate Religionis Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae, valde mihi placet, &amp;</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Ego eundem librum latine rurſus nunc editurio, additis pro man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſſa teſtimoniis, ad quae liber re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicit. Paro &amp; de jure belli ac pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis editionem novam, cum novorum teſtimoniorum, quos fine libri, anno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tationum
<pb facs="tcp:121169:67"/>vice, ſubnectam, ingenti acceſſione.</hi> Heinſiana <hi>ad Novum Teſtamentum ubi accepero, (expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cto autem in horas) cogitabo, an ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid nobis quod dicamus, reliqui fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerit. Quod</hi> Johannis Reigersber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gii, <hi>hoſpitis quondam tui, memor eſſe pergis, in eo rem mihi pergra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam, ac tua ſumma bonitate dignam facis: eſt is nunc in patria ſua, quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quo iturus eſt, circumlaturus ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per ſecum mentem plenam ſenſu be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficiorum tuorum. Literae viri ſupra omnem praedicationem poſiti, patris tui, multum hic leguntur. Si quas habes praeter editas, aut alio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum ad ipſum argumentoſiores, eas ſi publico dones, multos demerearis,
<pb facs="tcp:121169:67"/>me autem potiſſimum, ejus quae in ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo eluxit, pietatis ſimul atque erudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionis, maximum admiratorem. Mit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to tibi quas habet</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>ut Patris, ita tui amantiſſimus,</hi> Labbaeus. <hi>Si qua repererim alia, etiam eorum te faciam participem, ſemperque aut oſtendam, aut cupiam certe oſtendere, quanti &amp; maximum patrem fecerim, &amp; faciam ejus veſtigiis tam faelici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter inſistentemfilium.</hi> Lutetiae, 19. Septembris: M. DC. XXXIX.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Tuus toto animo, <hi>H. GROTI<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:121169:68"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
